<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Divine blossomes. A prospect or looking-glass for youth: wherein and whereby he may plainly behold and see a supereminency and super-excellency of grace and religion, beyond the worlds honor, glory, fame, repute, pleasure, joy, delight, love,. [sic] And all other lower accomodations whatsoever. Laid down to youth by exciting parallel between [brace] earths honor carnal pleasure inordinate love [brace] and [brace] heavens glory  and spiritual pleasure divine love. Under every of which particulars, the author exemplarily expresseth himself in a varied verse. / Composed by a hearty wel-wisher to the youthful generation, Francis Cockin, alias Cokayne.</title>
            <author>Cockin, Francis.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 161 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 66 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80028</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4873</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1652_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209121</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868019</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868019</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170222</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80028)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170222)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 207:E1652[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Divine blossomes. A prospect or looking-glass for youth: wherein and whereby he may plainly behold and see a supereminency and super-excellency of grace and religion, beyond the worlds honor, glory, fame, repute, pleasure, joy, delight, love,. [sic] And all other lower accomodations whatsoever. Laid down to youth by exciting parallel between [brace] earths honor carnal pleasure inordinate love [brace] and [brace] heavens glory  and spiritual pleasure divine love. Under every of which particulars, the author exemplarily expresseth himself in a varied verse. / Composed by a hearty wel-wisher to the youthful generation, Francis Cockin, alias Cokayne.</title>
                  <author>Cockin, Francis.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 118, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W.G. for E. Farnham, at the entrance into Popeshead-alley out of Cornhill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Earths .. Divine Love." connected on title page by a complex system of brackets.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 17".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Young men --  Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Young women --  Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>English poetry --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170222:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>DIVINE BLOSSOMES.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A PROSPECT or LOOKING-GLASS For YOUTH: Wherein and whereby he may plainly behold and ſee a Supereminency and Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excellency of <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> beyond the Worlds <hi>Honor, Glory, Fame, Repute, Pleaſure, Joy, Delight, Love,</hi> And all other lower Accommodations whatſoever.</p>
                  <p>Laid down to Youth by Exciting Parallel</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>Between <hi>Earths Honor</hi> and <hi>Heavens Glory</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Between <hi>Carnal Pleaſure</hi> and <hi>Spiritual Pleaſure</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Between <hi>Inordinate Love</hi> and <hi>Divine Love.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Under every of which particulars, the Author Exemplarily expeſſeth himſelf in a varied verſe.</p>
                  <p>Compoſed by a hearty Wel-wiſher to the Youthful Generation, FRANCIS COCKIN, <hi>aliàs</hi> COKAYNE.</p>
                  <q>Remember thy Creator in the dayes of thy Youth,</q>
                  <bibl>Eccl. 12.</bibl>
                  <q>Delight thy ſelf in the Lord, and he ſhall give thee thy Hearts deſire,</q>
                  <bibl>Pſal. 35. 4.</bibl>
                  <q>I love them that love me, and they that ſeek me early ſhall find me,</q>
                  <bibl>Prov. 8.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>W. G.</hi> for <hi>E. Farnham,</hi> at the entrance into <hi>Popeſhead-alley</hi> out of <hi>Cornhill,</hi> 1657.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170222:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:170222:2"/>
                  <head>To the Generation of Youth.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>TEnder Reader, knowing how much youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full yearts delight in eating early fruit, (though green and ſo unwholſome) I therefore here preſent thee with a diſh of early fruit, (yet mature and ripe, and therefore no whit dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to thy greedy ſtomack,) therefore accept it willingly and (with ſafety) fall to with courage.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And much good may it do thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Onely let me requeſt thee to uſe civill behaviour in thy ſo doing: be ſober, be ſerious, read under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandingly, apply diligently, and practiſe conſciona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly the precepts here given thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For thy good profit and incouragement, I have vouchſafed to expreſſe my ſelf unto thee; what thou haſt heard of me, by me, in me, and from me, do therefore and take all in Love from him, that ſeeks moſt heartily (and with the ſtrength of his Soul) thy eternal wellfare and Gods glory in thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Ely <date>July. 1656.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>F. C.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170222:3"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:170222:3"/>
                  <head>To the moſt famous &amp; renowned Mr. <hi>George Wither.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LL happineſs and peace I wiſh you: And ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been very deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous (ſince the firſt time I ever met with ought of yours) to gratifie you according to your worth and deſert; and finding no means and wayes thereunto, I have deigned to preſent theſe few Pages unto you, thereby to teſtifie (in part) the high eſteem and honorable reſpect that I adjudge you worthy of.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:170222:4"/>
                  <p>Sir, accept of this in love, paſs your candid cenſure of it, and though the Phraſes and Style be mean, let the Matter and Drift excuſe it. Again, conſidering by me 'twas penn'd (in a few dayes) with much haſte, and paſt from me immediately, no perſon fitter then your ſelf to patronize theſe Art<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Lines, could I find, becauſe your Youthful years were in the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſpent.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Sir, I am Yours, moſt ready to ſerve you in ought, FRANCIS COKAINE.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="publishers_advertisement">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170222:4"/>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LEt me requeſt thee when ever thou findeſt any fault in the ſenſe or Verſe, to mend it as is hereunder ſpecified; the Authors abſence having occaſioned ſeveral miſtakes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <p>PAg. 1. Staff. 4. l. 4. <hi>ſtrange</hi> r. <hi>ſtrong,</hi> ſt. 5. l. 2. <hi>in ſlaviſh</hi> r. <hi>give ſlaviſh</hi> p. 12. ſt. 3. l. 3. r. <hi>ſcatter'd ſtrength,</hi> p. 19. ſt. 30. l 2. r. <hi>with thoſe,</hi> p. 20. ſt. 34. l. 5. <hi>Joy</hi> r. <hi>Toy,</hi> p. 25. ſt. 54. 4. <hi>redeem</hi> r. <hi>eſteem,</hi> p. 29. ſt. 70. <hi>Heads</hi> r. <hi>Heſtos,</hi> p. 31. ſt. 79. l. 3. <hi>uſe</hi> r. <hi>caſe,</hi> p. 32. ſt. 82. l. 1. <hi>beſides</hi> r. <hi>repel or reſiſt,</hi> p. 33. ſt. 87. l. 6. <hi>months</hi> r. <hi>moments,</hi> p. 34. ſt. 90. l. 5. r. <hi>laviſh cups,</hi> p. 42. ſt. 98. l. 6. <hi>never</hi> r. <hi>ever,</hi> p. 45. ſt. 110. l. 6. <hi>be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ded bow</hi> r. <hi>bend and bow,</hi> p. 66. ſt. 24. l. 6. r. <hi>but dim,</hi> p. 69. ſt. 34. l 3. <hi>was pric'd,<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> p. 92. ſt. 13. 3. r. <hi>ſure ſmall diſpute,</hi> p. 93. ſt. 16. l 4. <hi>ful poſſeſſor</hi> p. 94. ſt. 20. l. 1. r. <hi>Queer of Heaven,</hi> p. 117. ſt. 30. l 7. r. <hi>motions.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="table_of_contents">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170222:5"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:170222:5"/>
                  <head>The Contents of the Book.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>FIrſt the invocation (preſents it ſelf) wherein the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour craves Gods divine aſſiſtance and gracious ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance in and of the intended work.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Then by way of Introduction proves his own fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>neſſe to the worke. Gives a word or two to Parents about the edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating their children, and declares the manner of their greeting them in Hell; hintes ſome matters to Superiors, and ſo procceds to the work it ſelf.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Wherein the Authour.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Firſt, begins to excite youth, to ſeek after God and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, from the heat of his Spirit aſpiring to honour, declares the high worth of the engagement.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>And foraſmuch as the heart of youth is ambitious of fame glory and renown gotten and won by valiancy in deſperate and dangerous attempts, therefore the Author deſcribes the might, ſtrength and power of that grand Chriſtian enemy.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:170222:6"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>And ſtirs up the courage of youth, to engage in the quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel againſt him, by ſeveral encouraging motives.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Declares the worth of that that lies at ſtake and muſt elſe be loſt, and then the worthy renown and glory that may be obtain'd, by a couragious encounter againſt fleſhly luſts.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>As alſo relates an Oneneſſe that is between Chriſts Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and the Spirit of him that oppoſes the motions of ſin, they both joyn to do the ſame work &amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Shews that according to the employment, ſo ſhould the reward be.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Then for the further encouragement, and ſtronger ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citement of youth, to ſeek God and Glory, the Author ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes himſelf, and declares at what a rate, he ſets the ſervice of God; the contempt that he hath of the world and all things in the world, in reſpect of that honourable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>By a brief ſurvey of all that the world affordeth he proves and declares all therein to be non-ſatisfactory, and inſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to the deſire of the Soul of man.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Then inſiſting upon the ſecond point, viz. pleaſure;</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Firſt, he ſhews the congruity that is between it, and the nature of youth, declares the effects of pleaſures, and to what they tend by inſtance.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>And gives ſound counſell therefrom, to youth in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of Soul-demeanment.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Then the Author layes down the riſt of pleaſure, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring what it is that makes pleaſure.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>And ſhews by ſimilitude the woful and dangerous eſtate of a vain luxurious Spirit.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Declares in a word or two the unmatchleſſe worth of the
<pb facs="tcp:170222:6"/> Soul, and reaſons ſomwhat from that thence its freedome.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>In ſadneſſe of heart declaring the abaſement of the Soul by ſin, hints at the reward of ſin by way of arguing.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Proves the ſoul Chriſts purchaſe, and diſcourſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what therefrom; Then layes down ſome Solid inſtructions to youth, how and whereby he ſhould get free from ſinnes ſlavery, and get the conqueſt of every helliſh enormity.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Deſcribes the bliſs that thereby his ſoul ſhall procure to it ſelf; viz. the preſence of Chriſt and ſanctification by his Spirit, acceptance of God through him, and adornment with his graces; lays down the paralell of the preſent eſtate with the eſtate paſt, and deſcribes ſome excellent peculiar Chriſtian privileges.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Then deſcribes pleaſure to be a painted ſtrumpet; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds 4 Queſtions to youth, from whence he gives him to underſtand how dear bought all the pleaſures of ſin are.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Deſcribes the miſerable ſlavery and ſervitude of ſin.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>And then for the delight of the Reader, the Authour varies that verſe, and expreſſes his own youthfull expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of pleaſure, ſhewing what it truely is;</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>And then declares and layes down the arguments and conſiderations wherewithall he oppoſed all the pleaſures of ſin, and got maſtery thereof.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hints to what ſin deprives of, and layes down, in a word or two, the excellencie of the unpa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>aleld ſweets of religion.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Then coming to the third particular ſhews thereunder, how youths heated bloud layes him open to love, and luſts. Declares the advantage the Devil takes at youths careleſſe activity; and how he ever attendeth to give him an object for his active Spirit to fix on.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:170222:7"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Shews youth to be guided by a head-ſtrong paſſion.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Then paralells Heavens beauty with earths, and divine with carnall love in ſeveral circumſtances.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Reaſons youth from the excellency of the one and the ſordidneſſe of the other, to ſeek that which is moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, eſchew abſurditie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> and dangers, the which is illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by ſeveral reſemblances.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Then the Authour turns off, and in a pleaſant ſtrain ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes himſelf, relating the excellency of divine beauty, and deſcribes the worthyneſs of divine Love by his own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, triumphing in his youthfull choyce.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Therein paralelling the beauty, excellency, proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe, ſweetneſſe, &amp;c. of the Creatours Love to the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in a kind of Soul-raviſhing extaſy, relating Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enamoring rarities.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Then comes to a concluſion, wherein he ſhews the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between the ſervice of ſin and God: excites from ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral conſiderations to the ſervice of God.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Relates the ſum of his own deſired endevour for the good of youth: how ſingle-hearted he hath been therein, affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately expreſſing the tenderneſſe of his heart to the good of young One.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>But more eſpecially, how exceeding precious gracious young-Ones are to him, and how entirely beloved by him.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Deign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> out of depth of affection to give them ſome pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar inſtructions.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Exhorts to make uſe of prayer; ſhews the excellency there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in it ſelf, and in its effects.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Relates his own experience thereof, and ſo therein and therewithall puts period to the whole.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="invocation">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170222:7"/>
                  <head>The Invocation.</head>
                  <lg n="1">
                     <head>[1.]</head>
                     <l>MOſt deareſt Lord! My ſouls deſire and joy,</l>
                     <l>That ſe'ſt and ruleſt all things even as one,</l>
                     <l>In whom it lies to ſave, or to deſtroy,</l>
                     <l>There being none can ſave, but thou alone:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="2">
                     <head>[2.]</head>
                     <l>'Tis thou alone, to whom I make my ſuit,</l>
                     <l>'Tis thou to whom my ſelf I do addreſſe;</l>
                     <l>'Tis for thy ſake that I would not be mute,</l>
                     <l>I'd ſpeak thy praiſe, nor can I do ought leſſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="3">
                     <head>[3.]</head>
                     <l>My tender youth proffers my ſlender Rimes</l>
                     <l>To do thee ſervice, whoſe I wholly am:</l>
                     <l>I give my beſt, I'd ſpend my vacant times</l>
                     <l>For and to thee, from whom my Being came:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="4">
                     <head>[4.]</head>
                     <l>Lord, mayſt thou pleaſe my fancy to enrich,</l>
                     <l>And fill my ſpirit with celeſtial flames,</l>
                     <l>Begetting in each faculty an itch</l>
                     <l>Of ſtrange deſire thereto, that whoſo blames</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="5">
                     <head>[5.]</head>
                     <l>Me, for the laying out my ſelf about</l>
                     <l>That which may tend thee honor for to bring,</l>
                     <l>I may them ſleight, in ſlaviſh thoughts the rout,</l>
                     <l>And in deſpite of all thy glories ſing.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="6">
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:170222:8"/>
                     <head>[6.]</head>
                     <l>Inſtruct my heart, and fill my Mind with Matter,</l>
                     <l>My Apprehenſion quicken, and enable;</l>
                     <l>Compoſe my Thoughts, let not Diſtraction tatter</l>
                     <l>My inner Man, but in Thee make me ſtable.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="7">
                     <head>[7.]</head>
                     <l>Yea, ad thou Art to poliſh ſo my Rimes,</l>
                     <l>That my intended purpoſe they may do:</l>
                     <l>Thou tak'ſt the advantage of all Things and Times</l>
                     <l>Here take thy 'dvantage, that thy Glories ſo</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="8">
                     <head>[8.]</head>
                     <l>May grow by my endevours, which when I</l>
                     <l>With joyful heart, with gladded ſoul ſhall ſee,</l>
                     <l>My utmoſt Aim and End I then eſpie:</l>
                     <l>(Oh may I not in this deceived bee!)</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="9">
                     <head>[9.]</head>
                     <l>For what doth't profit me, O Lord, to live,</l>
                     <l>If to thy praiſe my Life be noe directed?</l>
                     <l>Thou daily giv'ſt, I daily do receive,</l>
                     <l>Unworthy I, of Thee to be reſpected!</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="10">
                     <head>[10.]</head>
                     <l>A twofold wayes my Soul and Body's Thine,</l>
                     <l>Thine by Creation, Thine by Purchaſe too;</l>
                     <l>(By th' laſt of which thy Son and his is mine,</l>
                     <l>An intereſt in thy Self I have alſo.)</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="11">
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:170222:8"/>
                     <head>[11.]</head>
                     <l>A ſingle Bond ſufficient is to bind</l>
                     <l>An honeſt perſon to perform an Act;</l>
                     <l>And ſhall a double leſs advantage find?</l>
                     <l>How greatly diſ-ingenuous is that fact!</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="12">
                     <head>[12.]</head>
                     <l>Thine, thine I am, for thee I would lay out</l>
                     <l>My Strength, my Skill, my Might, my Power and Love:</l>
                     <l>Fain would I buſied be thy works about,</l>
                     <l>And for Employment now I do thee move.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="13">
                     <head>[13.]</head>
                     <l>My dappled Quill thy Service waits to do,</l>
                     <l>For to record whatere the Minde diſſolveth</l>
                     <l>To words, my hand is willing thereunto,</l>
                     <l>And all my Powers upon that task reſolveth.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="14">
                     <head>[14.]</head>
                     <l>Oh bleſs and breath upon my weak Endevours,</l>
                     <l>Thou God of bleſſing, Authour of all good,</l>
                     <l>That crown'ſt with glory that Soul that perſevers,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe might and power cannot be withſtood.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="15">
                     <head>[15.]</head>
                     <l>Infuſe thy Spirit ſo into my Soul,</l>
                     <l>That neither Wit nor matter may be wanting</l>
                     <l>Unto me, Youths vain courſes to controul,</l>
                     <l>And ſet his Nature after thee a panting.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="16">
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:170222:9"/>
                     <head>[16.]</head>
                     <l>For to inſinuate into his will,</l>
                     <l>And uſher thorough his Judgment to's Affection,</l>
                     <l>(Vouchſafe to me the Strength, the Art, the skill)</l>
                     <l>That He may give to Thee all due ſubjection.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="17">
                     <head>[17.]</head>
                     <l>Vouchſafe theſe feeble Lines for to inſpire</l>
                     <l>With ſo much power of thy prevailing Grace,</l>
                     <l>That they each Readers Heart may ſet on fire,</l>
                     <l>And efficacious be ſin to diſplace.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="18">
                     <head>[18.]</head>
                     <l>O God! Let not that Cannibal devoure</l>
                     <l>Thoſe precious Souls, for whom Chriſt gave his blood;</l>
                     <l>But mitigate his domineering power,</l>
                     <l>And make Mankind attentive more to good.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="19">
                     <head>[19.]</head>
                     <l>Permit him not, O Lord! to ſpoil and ſtroy</l>
                     <l>Thy tender Plants, nor any budding flower;</l>
                     <l>Permit him not thy vineyard to annoy,</l>
                     <l>Rebuke him, let him not thy vines devoure.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="20">
                     <head>[20.]</head>
                     <l>O let him not of Youth make a full prey!</l>
                     <l>Correct O Lord, Correct and give a check</l>
                     <l>To You<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h's vain courſes, ſtop 'm, make 'm ſtay,</l>
                     <l>For they'l conformed be to no ones beck:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="21">
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:170222:9"/>
                     <head>[21.]</head>
                     <l>Unblind Youths Eyes, unſtop his deafned Ears,</l>
                     <l>And undeceive his vain deceived Heart;</l>
                     <l>Strike thou his ſpirit, for he nothing fears,</l>
                     <l>And him and his beloved humours part:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="22">
                     <head>[22.]</head>
                     <l>Thou God of love and grace, ſhew mercy to him,</l>
                     <l>Vouchſafe to turn him, ere he goes to hell;</l>
                     <l>O let not luſts, pleaſures, vain love undo him,</l>
                     <l>Defeat him of thee, with the damn'd to dwell!</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="23">
                     <head>[23.]</head>
                     <l>But make him tractable to good Inſtruction,</l>
                     <l>Conformable unto thy bleſſed pleaſure,</l>
                     <l>Complyable to every ſafe direction,</l>
                     <l>And to eſteem thy love above all treaſure:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="24">
                     <head>[24.]</head>
                     <l>Make this my endevour ſerviceable to him,</l>
                     <l>Make this to him as pleaſant ſavoury food;</l>
                     <l>Yea, make it powerfull enough to woo him;</l>
                     <l>To purge out evils, make it phyſick good.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:170222:10"/>
                  <head>DIVINE BLOSSOMES.</head>
                  <div type="introduction">
                     <head>The Introduction.</head>
                     <lg n="1">
                        <head>[1.]</head>
                        <l>IF ſickly Men fitteſt Phyſicians are,</l>
                        <l>And troubled Conſciences the beſt Divines,</l>
                        <l>To contradict my fitneſs, then who dare,</l>
                        <l>To ſpeak to Youth in my unpoliſh'd Lines:</l>
                        <l>My years being tender, I experience do</l>
                        <l>What ere may be delightful Youth unto.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="2">
                        <head>[2.]</head>
                        <l>Who better knows, or who's a fitter Man</l>
                        <l>To tell the Road, than Carriers that do travel</l>
                        <l>It every day? Perhaps another can</l>
                        <l>Say what it was of late, and where ſome gravel</l>
                        <l>Was laid on ſuch a place, on ſuch a day;</l>
                        <l>But what at preſent 'tis, he cannot ſay.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="3">
                        <head>[3.]</head>
                        <l>But he that is a travelling each hour,</l>
                        <l>And ſeldome off the Road, can beſt diſcover</l>
                        <l>Each miry Bog: The like hath he the power</l>
                        <l>To do in any Art, that is a Lover</l>
                        <l>Thereof, and a ſound Student therein;</l>
                        <l>To which, and to his Nature, there's ſome kin.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="4">
                        <pb n="7" facs="tcp:170222:10"/>
                        <head>[4.]</head>
                        <l>My years being tender, and well neer their Bloom;</l>
                        <l>My blood being hot, and ſwelling in my veins;</l>
                        <l>Cares being ſtrangers, vigour taking room;</l>
                        <l>Who better may greet youth with pleaſant ſtrains?</l>
                        <l>Who better may deſcribe and ſpeak to 's Nature,</l>
                        <l>Than I that am a young and youthful Creature?</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="5">
                        <head>[5.]</head>
                        <l>Youth may ſay, Age layes too much burthen on them,</l>
                        <l>Having forgot what they in youth did do;</l>
                        <l>May think their ſolid precepts much may wrong them,</l>
                        <l>Or be too hard for Youth to attain unto:</l>
                        <l>There being diſparity in Age,</l>
                        <l>They may object, their counſel is too ſage.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="6">
                        <head>[6.]</head>
                        <l>But theſe and many other ſuch like cavils</l>
                        <l>Are ta'n away while youth to youth doth ſpeak;</l>
                        <l>Young ones beſt know what young ones ſooneſt gravels</l>
                        <l>Their folly, their vain courſes, where they'r weak:</l>
                        <l>There's a propenſity in youthful nature,</l>
                        <l>Congruity in almoſt every feature.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="7">
                        <head>[7.]</head>
                        <l>What ſhall I ſay to youthful years Abuſes?</l>
                        <l>Them to deſcribe, ſhould I now make my task,</l>
                        <l>Taking away their vain and fond Excuſes,</l>
                        <l>Too much time, pains, and labour would it ask:</l>
                        <l>Again, then muſt I old Age blame and check,</l>
                        <l>'Cauſe they neglected (careleſly) to deck.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="8">
                        <pb n="8" facs="tcp:170222:11"/>
                        <head>[8.]</head>
                        <l>Their Childrens tender years with virtues veil,</l>
                        <l>Which is the cauſe their Lives are now ſo bad,</l>
                        <l>For Virtue might as well in Youth prevail,</l>
                        <l>If that her ſolid precepts they had had:</l>
                        <l>Train up a Childe with precepts good and ſage,</l>
                        <l>And he will not forget the ſame in Age.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="9">
                        <head>[9.]</head>
                        <l>But how can Youth, Alas! how can he chuſe</l>
                        <l>But vile and vain diſordered Courſes take?</l>
                        <l>When as his Parent never did him uſe</l>
                        <l>To contradict, nor good to him to ſpeak:</l>
                        <l>Ground ſown with Nettles cannot bring forth Wheat,</l>
                        <l>He's like to thrive that eateth dirt for meat.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="10">
                        <head>[10.]</head>
                        <l>Oh Parents! what account d'ye think to make</l>
                        <l>To great <hi>Jehov</hi>' at the great Judgement-day?</l>
                        <l>Oh! how will ye appear? what can ye ſpeak?</l>
                        <l>The want of precepts made your Children ſtray:</l>
                        <l>Their language then'll be this, when they ſhall ſee ye,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Oh curſed Parents! Curſed, curſed be ye.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="11">
                        <head>[11.]</head>
                        <l>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>d it not been for you, we had not come</l>
                        <l>Into this place of Soul-tormenting pain,</l>
                        <l>You made us guilty of this heavy doom,</l>
                        <l>In that you cheriſh'd us in courſes vain:</l>
                        <l>You might have been the means of our Salvation,</l>
                        <l>But you have been the means of our Damnation.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="12">
                        <pb n="9" facs="tcp:170222:11"/>
                        <head>[12.]</head>
                        <l>Curſed be you with an eternal curſe,</l>
                        <l>Curs'd be the time wherein you us begat,</l>
                        <l>Curs'd be the wombe that bore's, ſhe that did's nurſe,</l>
                        <l>Curs'd be all they that much rejoyc'd at</l>
                        <l>Our Birth and Being: miſerable we</l>
                        <l>That are confin'd in Torments e'r to be.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="13">
                        <head>[13.]</head>
                        <l>Oh curſed Parents! you the woful cauſe</l>
                        <l>Of this our woful caſe moſt truly were,</l>
                        <l>In that you let us violate Gods laws,</l>
                        <l>Neglected to inſtruct us in his fear:</l>
                        <l>Curſed we ſay, for ever curs'd be you,</l>
                        <l>Becauſe the means of this our curſe are you.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="14">
                        <head>[14.]</head>
                        <l>You cocker'd, when you ſhould have us inſtructed;</l>
                        <l>You brought us up in vanity and ſin,</l>
                        <l>You laught with us, when you ſhould's corrected,</l>
                        <l>And that encourag'd us our courſes in:</l>
                        <l>You lookt not to us with an eye ſevere,</l>
                        <l>We never from you did ſound precepts hear.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="15">
                        <head>[15.]</head>
                        <l>Parents, what think ye of this woful greeting?</l>
                        <l>Is't nothing for to bed in flames of fire?</l>
                        <l>And be ſaluted at your heavy meeting</l>
                        <l>With ſtripes &amp; ſtrokes, with whips of knotted wire?</l>
                        <l>Look for no leſs, your children will do ſo,</l>
                        <l>What will not black Revenge fierce iury do?</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="15">
                        <pb n="10" facs="tcp:170222:12"/>
                        <head>[15.]</head>
                        <l>Bowels of love are turned there to hate,</l>
                        <l>Your Children are transformed into Devils;</l>
                        <l>I can't conceive, my Pen cannot relate</l>
                        <l>How they'l torment ye' for thoſe forbid Evils</l>
                        <l>That they did learn from your vain converſation,</l>
                        <l>Which greatly did conduce to their damnation.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="16">
                        <head>[16.]</head>
                        <l>Indeed, Can they do leſs then torture you</l>
                        <l>That were the cauſe that they are thus tormented?</l>
                        <l>Parents, Remember this, Conſider now</l>
                        <l>In time, leſt your damnation be augmented</l>
                        <l>By their company in thoſe fierce flames</l>
                        <l>That ever burn, and nought their fury tames.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="17">
                        <head>[17.]</head>
                        <l>Your greateſt Duty lie not in providing</l>
                        <l>Them here a portion, and in laying up</l>
                        <l>Such things for them, as if they'd here abiding</l>
                        <l>For evermore, and ſhould not taſte the Cup</l>
                        <l>That's in Gods hand, containing Wine that's red</l>
                        <l>(For them that know him not) by's fury bred.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="18">
                        <head>[18.]</head>
                        <l>But I do not intend to task my Muſe</l>
                        <l>At preſent, for to ſpeak unto old Age;</l>
                        <l>No, at the preſent I the ſame refuſe,</l>
                        <l>Yet ſhall my matter be both grave and ſage:</l>
                        <l>'Tis Youth to whom I do intend my ſpeech,</l>
                        <l>'Tis Youth I do as Auditor beſeech.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="19">
                        <pb n="11" facs="tcp:170222:12"/>
                        <head>[19.]</head>
                        <l>I ſhall not read Lectures of good Behaviour</l>
                        <l>Now unto Age, how they ſhould wiſely live;</l>
                        <l>How act themſelves, that all their acts might ſavour</l>
                        <l>Of Good; a good Example for to give</l>
                        <l>To imitative Youth, that notes each thing</l>
                        <l>They do, and does the like in many a thing.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="20">
                        <head>[20.]</head>
                        <l>And though I have hinted, yet I have no more</l>
                        <l>Than given an hint of that ſame weighty charge</l>
                        <l>Of Childrens Education, on the ſcore</l>
                        <l>Of thoſe that keep them, thoſe of riper age:</l>
                        <l>Thoſe acts of yours, that you think time doth ſmother,</l>
                        <l>Are kept alive, being acted by another.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="21">
                        <head>[21.]</head>
                        <l>'Tis Goſpel-Exhortation, BE DISCREET,</l>
                        <l>(As well to Youth as Age directly given)</l>
                        <l>'Tis not to one, but doth both Sexes greet,</l>
                        <l>Speaks to all perſons that look after Heaven:</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Be circumſpect and wiſe, Redeem the time,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>You that would live in that all-glorious Clime.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="22">
                        <head>[22.]</head>
                        <l>Old Age, remember, God doth notice take</l>
                        <l>Of al your words, your geſtures, thoughts and deeds,</l>
                        <l>Of each of which you muſt a reckoning make;</l>
                        <l>From <hi>Thoughts</hi> come <hi>Word,</hi> and from thence <hi>Action</hi> breeds:</l>
                        <l>God views your Generation, Children, ſee</l>
                        <l>The Devils mind, then ſee you wary bee.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="1">
                        <pb n="12" facs="tcp:170222:13"/>
                        <head>Excitations. [1.]</head>
                        <l>But tender Youth, Come hearken, lend an Ear;</l>
                        <l>My thoughts on you at preſent I do ſpend;</l>
                        <l>It is to you, to you I do declare</l>
                        <l>That which unto Soul-ſafety much doth tend:</l>
                        <l>Now thou art young, and ſound, and ſtrong in ſtature,</l>
                        <l>Remember, Oh Remember thy Creator.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="2">
                        <head>[2.]</head>
                        <l>Begin betimes to ſeek the King of glory,</l>
                        <l>At whoſe right hand pleaſures for evermore</l>
                        <l>Do bide and dwell, whoſe worth the Angels ſtory,</l>
                        <l>And they with Saints and Seraphims adore:</l>
                        <l>Up, up Youth, and purſue this glorious prize;</l>
                        <l>Shake, ſhake off ſloth, come quickly, quickly riſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="3">
                        <head>[3.]</head>
                        <l>Thy blood is hot (Youth) let that heat excite thee,</l>
                        <l>And ſtir thy ſpirits, move them to a flame;</l>
                        <l>Collect thy ſpirits ſtrength, here's that will fight thee;</l>
                        <l>Ariſe, ariſe, thy ſloth I greatly blame:</l>
                        <l>'Tis Glory, 'tis a Kingdome, 'tis laid down,</l>
                        <l>The brows of the victorious for to crown.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="4">
                        <head>[4.]</head>
                        <l>Come, here are brave attempts, noble atchievements,</l>
                        <l>Here, here's the way, the way to purchaſe honor;</l>
                        <l>Here's truly noble, truely brave employments,</l>
                        <l>To be a Souldier under Chriſts owne Banner:</l>
                        <l>The God of Heaven and Earth the Captain is,</l>
                        <l>The cauſe is good, 'tis for eternal bliſs.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="5">
                        <pb n="13" facs="tcp:170222:13"/>
                        <head>[5.]</head>
                        <l>O put on courage! Let that boyling blood</l>
                        <l>That heats your veins, turn into holy rage;</l>
                        <l>Bid Sin avaunt, let Sathan be withſtood,</l>
                        <l>And in that holy War your ſelves engage:</l>
                        <l>Redeem your time, your freedomes, and your ſelves,</l>
                        <l>For all are Captives unto helliſh Elves.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="6">
                        <head>[6.]</head>
                        <l>Your enemy is ſtrong, a potent foe,</l>
                        <l>He's full of might, of policy and skill;</l>
                        <l>The World, the Fleſh do joyn their ſtrength un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>,</l>
                        <l>Moſt earthly Powers do obey his will:</l>
                        <l>Things that do look with ſeeming glorious faces,</l>
                        <l>Principalities and Foes in heavenly places</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="7">
                        <head>[7.]</head>
                        <l>You have to fight againſt: Engines of War</l>
                        <l>Your Foe-man hath, ſleights, ſtratagems and wildes,</l>
                        <l>Whereby he often conquers from afar,</l>
                        <l>And often many Creatures he beguiles:</l>
                        <l>We are his Slaves, and in fell bondage all,</l>
                        <l>Stand at his beck, and run when he doth call.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="8">
                        <head>Encouragements [8.] and Exhortations.</head>
                        <l>Oh let us rouze us, quitting ſinful floth,</l>
                        <l>And put on courage, and go forth with might;</l>
                        <l>For to engage in fight, let's not be loth,</l>
                        <l>Becauſe we loſe our Souls elſe, and their right:</l>
                        <l>What though our Foe be ſtrong, our Captain's ſtronger:</l>
                        <l>What though his arm be long? our Captain's longer.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="9">
                        <pb n="14" facs="tcp:170222:14"/>
                        <head>[9.]</head>
                        <l>The Body's broke, Up, up, and take the ſpoyl,</l>
                        <l>The Body of our foes puiſſant ſtrength,</l>
                        <l>Our noble Captain 'th given Death the foyl,</l>
                        <l>And we ſhall be victorious to him at length:</l>
                        <l>Fall on, Fall on, our foes are in a Rout,</l>
                        <l>The Victory is ours, out of doubt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="10">
                        <head>[10.]</head>
                        <l>Right noble Spirits, true heroick Minds,</l>
                        <l>Delight t' engage where Courage may appear,</l>
                        <l>I have oft heard how glad He is that finds</l>
                        <l>A deſperate attempt, that may him dare;</l>
                        <l>And this they do, that the ſhrill Trump of Fame</l>
                        <l>Unto the Age may blazon forth their Name.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="11">
                        <head>[11.] Argument 1.</head>
                        <l>But young Men, Heark ye, If that airy honour</l>
                        <l>May move hot Spirits to adventure far,</l>
                        <l>Then what may this under <hi>Jehovah</hi>'s Banner</l>
                        <l>(For your owne Intereſts) t' attempt a War?</l>
                        <l>Y' are Slaves to Sin, and to each Humour; then</l>
                        <l>Ariſe, ariſe, and quit your ſelves like Men.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="12">
                        <head>[12.]</head>
                        <l>The Spoyl is good, the Triumph and the Joy</l>
                        <l>Is great and glorious, Ever doth endure;</l>
                        <l>Time ſha'nt wear out, Oblivion ſha'nt deſtroy</l>
                        <l>Your Trophees of Renown, you ſhall be ſure</l>
                        <l>Ever to have, and therewithall a Crown</l>
                        <l>Of laſting Glory, when this life's laid down.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="13">
                        <pb n="15" facs="tcp:170222:14"/>
                        <head>[13.]</head>
                        <l>Each valiant Act, and each Heroick Deed</l>
                        <l>You do, or ever ſhall attempt to do</l>
                        <l>With real Heart, taking reſpective heed,</l>
                        <l>Shall much the glory of your Crown ad to:</l>
                        <l>For every Luſt you conquer and ſubdue</l>
                        <l>Joy, Peace, and Comfort will to you enſue.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="14">
                        <head>[14.] Argument 2.</head>
                        <l>Nay, 'Tis high Honour for you then to joyn</l>
                        <l>With Gods own Son, the Heir of Earth and Heaven,</l>
                        <l>Your ſpirits then with his Spirit combine,</l>
                        <l>For to deſtroy all Sin his Life was given:</l>
                        <l>He came to overthrow the works of th' Devil,</l>
                        <l>The ſame do you, when you oppoſe an Evil.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="15">
                        <head>[15.]</head>
                        <l>Youth, would'ſt have Honour? Prethee tell me then,</l>
                        <l>What is't to be Favourite to a King?</l>
                        <l>The King of Kings, that rules and reigneth when</l>
                        <l>The world ſhall ceaſe, and every earthly thing:</l>
                        <l>This thou ſhalt be, if thou doſt to him live:</l>
                        <l>A Crown and Kingdome likewiſe he'l thee give.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="16">
                        <head>[16.]</head>
                        <l>Tell me then, Can thy ſtrength be laid out better?</l>
                        <l>Can thy hot vigorous Youth it ſelf imploy</l>
                        <l>For more advantage, then to make him Debter</l>
                        <l>Unto thee, that doth Heaven and Earth enjoy:</l>
                        <l>His Love thou gain'ſt by living in his will</l>
                        <l>Shalt Him and his poſſeſſe on <hi>Zions</hi> Hill.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="12">
                        <pb n="16" facs="tcp:170222:15"/>
                        <head>[12.]</head>
                        <l>Oh lay not out the ſtrength of youthful years</l>
                        <l>To feed foul humours, and a fond deſire,</l>
                        <l>Vain pleaſures will procure eternal tears,</l>
                        <l>And make thee lodge in everlaſting fire:</l>
                        <l>Reſiſt, oppoſe thy youthful inclination</l>
                        <l>That leads thee captive to each ſordid paſſion.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="13">
                        <head>[13.]</head>
                        <l>Wilt ſerve him whom thou art aſham'd to own,</l>
                        <l>As Maſter of the work that thou doſt do?</l>
                        <l>Be not deceiv'd, but look what thou haſt ſown</l>
                        <l>Thou canſt not but expect to reap alſo:</l>
                        <l>Bur-ſeed doth Burs, Dill-ſeed doth Dill bring forth,</l>
                        <l>The fruit and ſeed are ever of like worth.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="14">
                        <head>[14.]</head>
                        <l>Thou ſow'ſt in Fleſh, of Fleſh thou ſhalt reap ſhame;</l>
                        <l>But if in Spirit, glory thou ſhalt find;</l>
                        <l>Permit not puny pleaſure for to maim</l>
                        <l>Thy Souls beſt ſtrength, nor to enerve thy Mind:</l>
                        <l>Thou canſt not ſay but 'tis an abſurd evil</l>
                        <l>To give the worſt to God, the beſt to th' Devil.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="15">
                        <head>[15.]</head>
                        <l>Tax me not Young-man, that I do enjoyn</l>
                        <l>Thee to a thing impoſſible to do;</l>
                        <l>No, I'l aſſure thee, here is not a line</l>
                        <l>But 'tis thy ſafety to comply unto:</l>
                        <l>'Tis not by Hear-ſay that the thing I tell,</l>
                        <l>But by Experience I know it well.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <lg n="21">
                        <pb n="17" facs="tcp:170222:15"/>
                        <head>[21.]</head>
                        <l>My heart eſteems't the nobleſt deſign,</l>
                        <l>That ere my youth can make adventure on,</l>
                        <l>Unto <hi>Jehove</hi> to make a full reſign,</l>
                        <l>And in my Soul for to ſet up his Throne:</l>
                        <l>I would that he ſhould reign o're me as King,</l>
                        <l>And every thought to his Subjection bring.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="22">
                        <head>[22.]</head>
                        <l>His ſervice I eſteem at ſuch a rate,</l>
                        <l>I would not leave it for to be a King,</l>
                        <l>An Emperour the mightyeſt Potentate</l>
                        <l>The Earth ere bore: I do eſteem that thing</l>
                        <l>Of far leſs worth in Splendor, far more dim,</l>
                        <l>Then for to be a Servant unto him.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="23">
                        <head>[23.]</head>
                        <l>I ſcorne a Crown, an Earthly Diadem,</l>
                        <l>The Scepter of this univerſe to ſway;</l>
                        <l>Compared with that matchleſſe glorious Gem</l>
                        <l>Of grace: for why that Honour's but a day.</l>
                        <l>But grace doth bring to glory evermore,</l>
                        <l>Makes a poſſeſſour of all glorious Store.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="24">
                        <head>[24.]</head>
                        <l>If that a Crown was layed at my feet,</l>
                        <l>As ſure as I do live, there ſhould it lie;</l>
                        <l>If with Emperial honour men ſhould greet</l>
                        <l>Me, as the greateſt Earthly majeſty;</l>
                        <l>I would refuſe that honour and that grace,</l>
                        <l>For thoſe ſame troubles that attend the place.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="25">
                        <pb n="18" facs="tcp:170222:16"/>
                        <head>[25.]</head>
                        <l>Much more would I contemn it, if it ſhould</l>
                        <l>Be proffer'd to me, if I would forſake</l>
                        <l>The Service of my God, or if I would</l>
                        <l>My ſelf ſubſervient to my humours make;</l>
                        <l>No, ſuch petty honour I diſown,</l>
                        <l>I eye no leſs then an alglorious Crown.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="26">
                        <head>[26.]</head>
                        <l>An Earthly Crown's too mean for my deſire,</l>
                        <l>Too baſe an object for my heart to fix on:</l>
                        <l>My Spirit's fill'd, with more Heroick fire,</l>
                        <l>I beauty love, not ſuch a dull complexion;</l>
                        <l>My Noble Soul doth crave a bigger boone,</l>
                        <l>I muſt injoy that ſacred Three in one.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="27">
                        <head>[27.]</head>
                        <l>Your fading honour I eſteem as dung,</l>
                        <l>Earth's weltering glory as the dirt in ſtreet;</l>
                        <l>I will not lodg one thought thereof among</l>
                        <l>Thoſe noble thoughts, my Soul do dayly greet;</l>
                        <l>Baſe ſervile earth, avaunt, I'l not enſlave</l>
                        <l>My thoughts with thee, if I the world might have.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="28">
                        <head>[28.]</head>
                        <l>Alas poor earth, what's all that thou canſt give,</l>
                        <l>Or doſt afford, when ſorrow greets the mind?</l>
                        <l>Wherein can an awakened conſcience live?</l>
                        <l>What cordial in thy Store-houſe can it find?</l>
                        <l>Thou canſt not give thereto one dram of peace;</l>
                        <l>'Tis not in thee to make diſtraction ceaſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="29">
                        <pb n="19" facs="tcp:170222:16"/>
                        <head>[29.]</head>
                        <l>Alas, Alas! thy glories are too mean.</l>
                        <l>Too mean an object, for the Souls deſire:</l>
                        <l>The Souls deſire's vaſt and too extreme,</l>
                        <l>'Tis too extreme, and heat with better fire,</l>
                        <l>Then to be quencht, then for to be contented,</l>
                        <l>What thoſe poor ſhadows that by thee's preſented.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="30">
                        <head>[30.]</head>
                        <l>Thy wealth, what's that a truſs of meer deceit,</l>
                        <l>A bladder full of wind, an empty joy,</l>
                        <l>A real nothing, yet a glorious baite,</l>
                        <l>That doth beguil man of eternal joy;</l>
                        <l>And ſhall my noble Spirit then lay out</l>
                        <l>Her precious thoughts, ſuch vanities about.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="31">
                        <head>[31]</head>
                        <l>No, No, my Soul's immortal, and muſt have,</l>
                        <l>Such wealth as is of an immortal being;</l>
                        <l>Such treaſures as indure for aye I crave,</l>
                        <l>What do'nt I lightly prize and value, ſeeing</l>
                        <l>It cannot anſwer my Souls vaſt deſire,</l>
                        <l>Allay nor coole the heat thereof the fire.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="32">
                        <head>[32.]</head>
                        <l>Thy pleaſures (world) thy Senſe-beſotting pleaſures,</l>
                        <l>That ſo bewitch's men of tender years:</l>
                        <l>Conduce as much to joy as do thy treaſures,</l>
                        <l>Unto contentment, and to free from fears;</l>
                        <l>But this is that, that moſt of 'th world do follow,</l>
                        <l>'Tis after pleaſure that they hoop and hollow.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="33">
                        <pb n="20" facs="tcp:170222:17"/>
                        <head>[33.]</head>
                        <l>'Tis pleaſure that doth take the heart of youth,</l>
                        <l>'Tis pleaſure his deſires lead him to;</l>
                        <l>His hot veins ſwel, and pleaſure ſtrait doth ſooth,</l>
                        <l>His lively humours makes them act and go:</l>
                        <l>Pleaſures doth lull moſt younglings faſt aſleep,</l>
                        <l>Makes them laugh, now, eternally to weep.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="34">
                        <head>[34.]</head>
                        <l>O Young ones know Pleaſure's the Devils bait,</l>
                        <l>Wherewith he fiſhes for immortal ſouls;</l>
                        <l>In Pleaſure he doth lodge a grand deceit,</l>
                        <l>And ſo (moſt) youthfull Nature he befools;</l>
                        <l>Your boiling blood do ſooneſt cloſe with pleaſures,</l>
                        <l>Which of Gods wrath doth oft unlock the Treaſures.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="35">
                        <head>[35.]</head>
                        <l>Alas! and what are pleaſures to Gods Ire?</l>
                        <l>Pleaſures are fading that doth Age endure:</l>
                        <l>Think ye, can pleaſures coole thoſe flames of fire,</l>
                        <l>Or th' bitings of thoſe helliſh Scorpions Cure.</l>
                        <l>No your delightful pleaſures then will ſting ye,</l>
                        <l>As ſure as now they unto Hell will bring ye.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="36">
                        <head>[36.]</head>
                        <l>Pleaſure's a Ship that doth imbark for Hell</l>
                        <l>All Paſſengers that are contain'd therein;</l>
                        <l>In endleſs flames they muſt be ſure to dwell,</l>
                        <l>That do indulge and live and dye in ſin;</l>
                        <l>They ſweet and ſwiftly Sail, and that doth tend,</l>
                        <l>Quickly to bring 'em to their Iourneys end.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="37">
                        <pb n="21" facs="tcp:170222:17"/>
                        <head>[37.]</head>
                        <l>O ſtay thy courſe young man, lower thy Sails,</l>
                        <l>Winde up thy Canvas Ty 't cloſe to the Maſt:</l>
                        <l>(Being open ſpread the wind then moſt prevailes,)</l>
                        <l>Oh therefore wind it up and ty 't up faſt.</l>
                        <l>The affections are the Sailes, the which the Guſts;</l>
                        <l>Of vain deſires do fill full with wanton Luſts.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="38">
                        <head>[38.]</head>
                        <l>The Maſt I'd have thee tie theſe Sailes about,</l>
                        <l>Is Solid reaſon, and a judgment true:</l>
                        <l>Reaſon ſhould guide th'affections thoroughou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>,</l>
                        <l>And judgment ſhould inordinacy ſubdue;</l>
                        <l>Reaſon is Miſtris Governeſs, will, deſire, affection,</l>
                        <l>As hand-maids ſhould attend her in ſubjection.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="39">
                        <head>[39.]</head>
                        <l>But for to ſpeak more properly unto thee,</l>
                        <l>Reſpecting what delights moſt tender years;</l>
                        <l>Preventing pleaſures that they mayn't undo thee,</l>
                        <l>And ſo expoſe thee unto endleſſe tears;</l>
                        <l>I ſay Religion yields as much delight,</l>
                        <l>As ſinne can do, perſiſted in aright.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="40">
                        <head>[40.]</head>
                        <l>All pleaſure riſes from congruity,</l>
                        <l>And fitneſs 't<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>een the faculty and object;</l>
                        <l>When there's a natural propenſity,</l>
                        <l>Needs muſt it be a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>oſt delightful ſubject.</l>
                        <l>Guide then thy Soul by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>udgments ſolid Art,</l>
                        <l>What makes delight's the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>mper of the Heart?</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="41">
                        <pb n="22" facs="tcp:170222:18"/>
                        <head>[41.]</head>
                        <l>An earthly heart doth earthly things perſue,</l>
                        <l>An heaven-born Spirit takes delight in heaven:</l>
                        <l>From a luxurious heart there doth enſue</l>
                        <l>Luxuriouſneſs, (of vertue quite bereaven;)</l>
                        <l>An empty wanton heart filled with aire,</l>
                        <l>E'ry vaine object's ready for to dare.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="42">
                        <head>[42.]</head>
                        <l>And ſuch a heart like an un-ballaſt'd Ship,</l>
                        <l>Is turned o'r with e'ry breath of wind;</l>
                        <l>As empty veſſels under ſail do skip,</l>
                        <l>That they within 'm, nought but danger find,</l>
                        <l>So 's the immortal Spirit toſt to and fro;</l>
                        <l>Hurried up and down, where fancy wills to go.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="43">
                        <head>[43.]</head>
                        <l>This matchleſſe Gem, this noble worthy Pee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e,</l>
                        <l>Continually of ſhipwrack is in danger;</l>
                        <l>Toſt to and fro, now there, and ſometime here,</l>
                        <l>Unto all ſafety a perpetual ſtranger;</l>
                        <l>So long as mov'd by the light wind of paſſion,</l>
                        <l>Subject to nothing but to alteration.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="44">
                        <head>[44.]</head>
                        <l>Ineſtimable worth, value unknown.</l>
                        <l>And paſt conceiving is the Soul of man,</l>
                        <l>A treaſure, Jewel, that <hi>Jehove</hi> do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>h own,</l>
                        <l>Term ſo; and take delight in; tell me then,</l>
                        <l>Should this ſame peereleſs Spirit ſerve an humour,</l>
                        <l>A beſteal, ſordid luſt, it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>ngth conſumer.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="45">
                        <pb n="23" facs="tcp:170222:18"/>
                        <head>[45.]</head>
                        <l>The Soul's a heaven-born virgin proſtitute her</l>
                        <l>Wilt thou, to loathſome ſin and ſo to Hell?</l>
                        <l>Ah! canſt thou ſuffer Divells to deprive her,</l>
                        <l>Of ſtate, of glory, with them for to dwell?</l>
                        <l>Muſt Shee her countrey, and her kindred leave,</l>
                        <l>A curſed doome with Divels to receive?</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="46">
                        <head>[46.]</head>
                        <l>My heart doth ake to think of the abaſement</l>
                        <l>The Soul doth ſuffer, while it traide with ſin:</l>
                        <l>My Spirit ſobs to view that foul defacement,</l>
                        <l>Of <hi>J'hoves</hi> bright glorious beauty's ſeated in</l>
                        <l>The Soul of man; there ever to endure,</l>
                        <l>Conſiſting in an holy heart and pure.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="47">
                        <head>[47.]</head>
                        <l>Ah wanton youth, are earths vain worthleſs pleaſures</l>
                        <l>So dear unto thee, that thou't not them leave;</l>
                        <l>For feare of great <hi>Jehovahs</hi> direful treaſures,</l>
                        <l>Nor yet a Crown of glory to receive?</l>
                        <l>Wilt thou ſell life and glory for a toy,</l>
                        <l>For ſordid pleaſure barter heavenly joy?</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="65">
                        <head>[65.]</head>
                        <l>Ah canſt thou be content to bed in flames,</l>
                        <l>In utter darkneſs to make thine abode?</l>
                        <l>Canſt thou dwel there where nothing fury tames,</l>
                        <l>Eternally deprived of thy God?</l>
                        <l>Ah canſt thou bear the burthen of Gods Ire,</l>
                        <l>When as that task ſhall never out expire.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="49">
                        <pb n="24" facs="tcp:170222:19"/>
                        <head>[49.]</head>
                        <l>O youth remember thine immortal Soul,</l>
                        <l>And beare in mind what price was for it given!</l>
                        <l>Remember what can purge it being foule,</l>
                        <l>Conſider what may bring it unto Heaven;</l>
                        <l>Gods onely Son had of it ſuch eſteem,</l>
                        <l>That with his death its life he did redeem.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="50">
                        <head>[50.]</head>
                        <l>For Chriſts ſake thou thy Souls Salvation prize,</l>
                        <l>Becauſe his death did life unto it give,</l>
                        <l>Permit not pleaſures to put out thy eyes,</l>
                        <l>But ronze thy ſloth, and up unto him live;</l>
                        <l>Live unto him whoſe death bought thy Salvation,</l>
                        <l>Die for his ſake whoſe Life's thy preſervation.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="51">
                        <head>[51.]</head>
                        <l>Oh die thou muſt, or thou canſt never live,</l>
                        <l>Die to thy ſelf, to thy hearts luſts and pleaſures;</l>
                        <l>Die to all ſinne, or thou canſt not receive,</l>
                        <l>Thoſe glorious ſweets that God to his out-meaſures</l>
                        <l>Thy Souls redemption coſt Chriſts utmoſt breath,</l>
                        <l>And its Salvation muſt be by ſinns death.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="52">
                        <head>[52.]</head>
                        <l>Thou muſt be buried with him into death<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </l>
                        <l>Or thou canſt not in life with him partake:</l>
                        <l>That ſharp (two edged) cutting ſword unſheath,</l>
                        <l>To cut down luſts that ſeparation make</l>
                        <l>'Tween thee and him, 'tween his Spirit and Thine,</l>
                        <l>That do thee 'gainſt him unto ill incline.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="53">
                        <pb n="25" facs="tcp:170222:19"/>
                        <head>[53.]</head>
                        <l>Know, fleſhly luſts do war againſt the Soul,</l>
                        <l>And ſeek its utter ruin and undoing:</l>
                        <l>'Tis thy ſouls ſafety, Youth, them to controul,</l>
                        <l>But thou art ever courting and a wooing</l>
                        <l>Them with delight unto thee, thy deſires</l>
                        <l>Do beak themſelves at luſts baſe ſmoaky fires.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="54">
                        <head>[54.]</head>
                        <l>My Soul doth groan for to behold the Courſes</l>
                        <l>That young ones take; how they with full carere</l>
                        <l>Seek their own ruin, and as tender Nurſes,</l>
                        <l>Do nouriſh, cheriſh, and redeem as dear,</l>
                        <l>That which deprives them of a dwelling place,</l>
                        <l>In Heaven to behold Gods glorious face.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="55">
                        <head>[55.]</head>
                        <l>Luxurious youth, a little lend an Eare</l>
                        <l>To me, and I'l thee ſome few precepts give;</l>
                        <l>Be ſober minded then attend and heare:</l>
                        <l>Some rules I'l ſet thee down whereby to live;</l>
                        <l>Firſt guard thy heart with double diligence,</l>
                        <l>And let thine eye therein have reſidence.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="56">
                        <head>[56.]</head>
                        <l>And being ſober, then ſtrait look about,</l>
                        <l>For matter wherewithall t'employ thy mind;</l>
                        <l>Rouze up thy ſelf, give ſlaviſh thoughts the rout,</l>
                        <l>Let ſor did luſts within thee no place find;</l>
                        <l>Read ſacred writ, and meditate thereon,</l>
                        <l>Be ruminating ever thereupon.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="57">
                        <pb n="26" facs="tcp:170222:20"/>
                        <head>[57]</head>
                        <l>That looſe licentious Luſts may finde no room,</l>
                        <l>No place for entertainment in thy Soul,</l>
                        <l>That when (according to their wont) they come,</l>
                        <l>Thy minds imployment may their courſe controul</l>
                        <l>Oppoſe an Evil, and it ſha'n't orecome thee,</l>
                        <l>Reſiſt the Devil, and he will fly from thee.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="58">
                        <head>[58]</head>
                        <l>When ſaucy mirth, or any wanton luſt</l>
                        <l>Doth proffer thee a greeting any more,</l>
                        <l>Tell'em, you know 'em not, and that you muſt</l>
                        <l>Have no acquaintance with them as before</l>
                        <l>You had unto your coſt, when they did fool</l>
                        <l>Your noble ſpirit, bearing in it rule.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="59">
                        <head>[59]</head>
                        <l>Tell 'em that now you 'ave found a better Maſter,</l>
                        <l>And nobler ſervice for to pitch upon;</l>
                        <l>You'l ſeek to ſpare where you have been a waſter,</l>
                        <l>And will not do as you before have done;</l>
                        <l>When they do knock, tell 'm you a'n't at leiſure</l>
                        <l>To let 'em in, but bid 'em wait your pleaſure.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="60">
                        <head>[60]</head>
                        <l>And ſure I am that ſuch like entertaiment</l>
                        <l>As this, will cauſe bold Sin to hang its ears:</l>
                        <l>Theſe words or others of the like concernment</l>
                        <l>(Maintain'd with heart ſincere &amp; ardent Prayers)</l>
                        <l>Will make the Devil in thee hide his face,</l>
                        <l>Will overcome him, make him quit the place.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="61">
                        <pb n="27" facs="tcp:170222:20"/>
                        <head>[61]</head>
                        <l>And then <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> and his glorious Train</l>
                        <l>(By his Soul-ſanctifying Spirit) will</l>
                        <l>Enter thy heart, ſet up his Throne, and reign,</l>
                        <l>And all his bleſſed Pleaſure there fulfill;</l>
                        <l>He'll enter then, who is the Prince of Peace,</l>
                        <l>Triumphing gloriouſly will make Sin ceaſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="62">
                        <head>[62]</head>
                        <l>And as before thy Soul was a foul Cage</l>
                        <l>Of unclean Birds, a Stie of naſty Devils,</l>
                        <l>Hells Council-Chamber, and thy Acts Hells Stage,</l>
                        <l>Whereon thou didſt diſplay all inbred Evils;</l>
                        <l>Now 'tis become the Palace of a King,</l>
                        <l>The King of Glory, bleſt in every thing.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="63">
                        <head>[63]</head>
                        <l>Where Devils did in conſultation ſit,</l>
                        <l>(As they do always about acts unclean)</l>
                        <l>Malicious helliſh miſchiefs, which to beget</l>
                        <l>Not yet brought in action to be ſeen)</l>
                        <l>There Gods bleſs'd Spirit (Now) doth counſel give,</l>
                        <l>Unto the Soul diſport it ſelf and live.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="64">
                        <head>[64]</head>
                        <l>Note this, young Man, peruſe well the expreſſion,</l>
                        <l>Me thinks 'tſhould thy hot bloud convert to ſlames,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>JEHOVAH</hi> will not onely take poſſeſſion,</l>
                        <l>And dwell in thee, but alſo Son thee names;</l>
                        <l>He'll be thy Father, thou ſhalt be his Son,</l>
                        <l>Learn at all times to ſay, Thy will be done.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="65">
                        <pb n="28" facs="tcp:170222:21"/>
                        <head>[65.]</head>
                        <l>But that's not all, though that's a glorious favour,</l>
                        <l>To be a child to the eternal God:</l>
                        <l>I'le walk in thee: Oh here's a ſpeech doth favour</l>
                        <l>Of more then making with thee an abode;</l>
                        <l>My ſelf I'le joy refreſh, diſport, delight</l>
                        <l>In thee, ſayes the allglorious God of might.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="66">
                        <head>[66.]</head>
                        <l>For what doth walk, ſpeak leſs then recreation,</l>
                        <l>Delight, refreſhment, (not excluding) joy,</l>
                        <l>As alſo (oft 'tis) Soul accommodation,</l>
                        <l>Which ſenſes (here) don't Scripture truth deſtroy;</l>
                        <l>For Scripture doth the ſame to us commence,</l>
                        <l>What not in the ſame words, yet in the ſenſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="67">
                        <head>[67.]</head>
                        <l>But one thing more, youth, let me hint unto thee,</l>
                        <l>From this ſame text now I have touch'd upon:</l>
                        <l>God ſayes he'l dwel in thee, then let it woo thee</l>
                        <l>To ſay to Hell, Avaunt; to ſinne, Begone;</l>
                        <l>For he and ſin in one heart cannot dwel,</l>
                        <l>No more then thou can'ſt live at eaſe in Hell.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="68">
                        <head>[68.]</head>
                        <l>I'l walk in thee, the which expreſſion ſpeaks,</l>
                        <l>(As well as joy) that he'l take notice too</l>
                        <l>Of all thy acts, and all thoſe private tricks</l>
                        <l>That thou in ſecret undeſcry'd doſt do:</l>
                        <l>He that is alwayes walking round about</l>
                        <l>A houſe, can't chuſe but ſee what's done throughout.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="69">
                        <pb n="29" facs="tcp:170222:21"/>
                        <head>[69.]</head>
                        <l>But to come cloſer to the thing in hand,</l>
                        <l>I'le put it to thee, youngling for to judge;</l>
                        <l>Whether herein or ſinne moſt joy doth ſtand,</l>
                        <l>Peace this attending (too) but ſinne a ſcourge;</l>
                        <l>Sinne leads the Soul a dance, I ſigh to tell,</l>
                        <l>It here begins, but ends i'th' loweſt Hell.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="70">
                        <head>[70.]</head>
                        <l>Moreover youngling I can tell thee this,</l>
                        <l>That that which makes ſin lively to appear,</l>
                        <l>And doth bewitch thy Soul thereon, nought is,</l>
                        <l>But thoſe ſame borrowed garments ſhe doth wear</l>
                        <l>That ſhe hath ſtolen from vertue; whoſe they are,</l>
                        <l>As't will hereafter plainly appear.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="71">
                        <head>[71.]</head>
                        <l>There's but a painted ſtrumpet that doth lure</l>
                        <l>All perſons void of underſtanding to her;</l>
                        <l>Saw ye her in her night cloaths, I am ſure</l>
                        <l>She would affright ye, and you'd ceaſe to woo her;</l>
                        <l>She's deckt in vertues robes, and ſo ſhe's fine,</l>
                        <l>Yet at the beſt, ſhe's but a painted ſhrine.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="62">
                        <head>[62.]</head>
                        <l>But if vaine pleaſures muſt thy Miſtris be,</l>
                        <l>And have the ſervice of thy beſt affection,</l>
                        <l>Then thou to bed with her muſt ſure be,</l>
                        <l>Nor canſt thou that deny, ſince in ſubjection</l>
                        <l>To her thy Soul doth live, and acts her will,</l>
                        <l>And all her heads doſt faithfully fulfill.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="73">
                        <pb n="30" facs="tcp:170222:22"/>
                        <head>[73.]</head>
                        <l>Should I deſcribe the Bed, and the place where</l>
                        <l>The Bed is made, 'twould task my Muſe too hard,</l>
                        <l>But look where Devils dwell, the place is there,</l>
                        <l>The Bed it ſelf cann't be by me declar'd;</l>
                        <l>'Tis ſulphurous flames, 'tis torments ſharp and fell,</l>
                        <l>'Tis gnawing Conſcience, (in a word) 'tis Hell.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="74">
                        <head>[74.]</head>
                        <l>One word more youngling, wilt thou ſell thy ſight?</l>
                        <l>Or wilt thou for a price part with the light?</l>
                        <l>What wilt thou ask for this thy breathing right?</l>
                        <l>Or take, the world to be bought out of quite?</l>
                        <l>I know thy anſwer to theſe very well,</l>
                        <l>For ten worlds worth, thou none of theſe canſt ſell.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="75">
                        <head>[75.]</head>
                        <l>And I beleeve thou doſt abhor the thought</l>
                        <l>Of valuing of thoſe with any thing:</l>
                        <l>Nay, I beleeve thy Soul with ſorrows fraught,</l>
                        <l>When any doth theſe into queſtion bring:</l>
                        <l>I know young man, that here thou art ſo nice,</l>
                        <l>Thou loath'ſt to hear theſe valued at a price.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="76">
                        <head>[76.]</head>
                        <l>But foraſmuch as none theſe things may mention</l>
                        <l>Unto thee: Heark, I'le tell thee in thine ear,</l>
                        <l>And tell thee truth, for that's my hearts intention,</l>
                        <l>Thou overlov'ſt theſe, yet not count'ſt them dear,</l>
                        <l>For why, thou ſpend'ſt them on thy miſtris Pleaſure,</l>
                        <l>And laviſhly doſt waſte them out of meaſure.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="77">
                        <pb n="31" facs="tcp:170222:22"/>
                        <head>[77]</head>
                        <l>Nay, thou doſt ſell a Pearl worth all of theſe,</l>
                        <l>More precious Gems thou part'ſt with for her ſake</l>
                        <l>Than I can utter, that whoever ſees</l>
                        <l>That dangerous courſe that thou doſt for her take,</l>
                        <l>Cann't chuſe but ſay, Thou waſtes thy ſtrength, and ſight</l>
                        <l>Moſt wickedly, and ſo deſerv'ſt no light.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="78">
                        <head>[78.]</head>
                        <l>More plainly, is the light a pleaſant thing,</l>
                        <l>That thou'dſt not be depriv'd of for a world?</l>
                        <l>Then part with Sin, for elſe it will thee bring</l>
                        <l>Into perpetual darkneſs, to be hurl'd.</l>
                        <l>Thou ſhalt for evermore part with the light,</l>
                        <l>And be included in perpetual night.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="79">
                        <head>[79.]</head>
                        <l>Thy ſight is precious to thee, 'cauſe the light</l>
                        <l>Doth pleaſant objects unto it unfold,</l>
                        <l>But know in Hell the uſe is alter'd quite,</l>
                        <l>There's darkneſs, nought but terrours to behold;</l>
                        <l>So that for Sin both Light and Sight thou ſell'ſt,</l>
                        <l>Both Life and Joy, and for its ſake thou dwell'ſt</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="80">
                        <head>[80.]</head>
                        <l>Amidſt fierce fiery flames, and doſt debar</l>
                        <l>Thy Soul that bleſſed Privilege, to ſee</l>
                        <l>Gods glorious face, the which exceedeth far</l>
                        <l>What ere thy worldly intereſt to thee</l>
                        <l>Can give, and what's thy breathing right to this?</l>
                        <l>Breath well improv'd may make a gale to bliſs.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="81">
                        <pb n="3" facs="tcp:170222:23"/>
                        <head>[81.]</head>
                        <l>O youngling therefore if thou prizeſt ought</l>
                        <l>That's dear or good, why then ſhake hands with ſinne,</l>
                        <l>And be not by't into ſubjection brought,</l>
                        <l>Nor in its ſlavery continue in:</l>
                        <l>Pleaſures of ſin but for a moment are,</l>
                        <l>The purchaſe of them therefore's too too dear.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="82">
                        <head>[82.]</head>
                        <l>Beſides its motions, force them from thy Soul,</l>
                        <l>And hold no private conſultation with him:</l>
                        <l>Its riſing power betimes ſuppreſs, controule,</l>
                        <l>For growing great thou canſt not lightly will'm.</l>
                        <l>If any ſordid evill you'd entombe,</l>
                        <l>The readyeſt way's to kill it in the wombe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="83">
                        <head>[83.]</head>
                        <l>Give ſin no footing, for it will intrude,</l>
                        <l>'T will make its paſſage like a mighty ſtream;</l>
                        <l>Give 't but an entrance, and you ſtraight include</l>
                        <l>Ten times more inconvenience then you deem;</l>
                        <l>If entertained for a moneths ſpace,</l>
                        <l>It ſtraight becometh Maſter of the place.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="84">
                        <head>[84.]</head>
                        <l>'Tis a bold gueſt, and though a ſordid groome,</l>
                        <l>Too baſe to come within the Souls confines:</l>
                        <l>Yet takes it up the beſt and braveſt roome,</l>
                        <l>And further, all its forces ſtrength combines;</l>
                        <l>To keep the ſame, and there as Lord to reign,</l>
                        <l>Permitting it none elſe to entertain.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="85">
                        <pb n="33" facs="tcp:170222:23"/>
                        <head>[85.]</head>
                        <l>Sin's a moſt cruel Task-maſter to evil,</l>
                        <l>It giveth work, but gives no time to play,</l>
                        <l>Doth tyrannize as a moſt cruel Devil,</l>
                        <l>'Fording no intermiſſion Night nor Day:</l>
                        <l>Heart, hand, eys, ears, nor tongue, nor lips m'n't ſtound,</l>
                        <l>But eagerly perſiſt to run Sins round;</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="86">
                        <head>[86.]</head>
                        <l>The Eys muſt gaze the Heart to ſet on fire,</l>
                        <l>The Ear attends for to blow up the flame,</l>
                        <l>Which to expreſs the Tongue doth never tire,</l>
                        <l>And yet this Tyrant ſharply doth them blame,</l>
                        <l>Says they are idle, that they nothing do,</l>
                        <l>(When as their ſpirits faint, their work is ſo.)</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="87">
                        <head>[87.]</head>
                        <l>Here's Slavery exceeding <hi>Egypts</hi> Task,</l>
                        <l>They Brick muſt make, yet ſtore themſelves with Straw,</l>
                        <l>No eaſe, no reſpite, nor no help muſt ask,</l>
                        <l>But ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>r in yoke, like Slaves, like Horſes, draw:</l>
                        <l>From this to th' other ill the poor Soul trudges</l>
                        <l>From that for t' other Luſt the poor Soul drudges.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="88">
                        <head>[88.]</head>
                        <l>Yet ſo the Creature's fool'd, that it contents</l>
                        <l>It ſelf in this hard bondage; don't compl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>in</l>
                        <l>Of Servitude, nor in the leaſt repents,</l>
                        <l>But layeth out its ſtrength for to maintain</l>
                        <l>Theſe ſordid humours, and their lives to cheriſh,</l>
                        <l>Though for the ſame both Soul and Body periſh.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="89">
                        <pb n="34" facs="tcp:170222:24"/>
                        <head>[89.]</head>
                        <l>What doth the Drunkard prize above his Pots?</l>
                        <l>Who is more free than he? He doth not think</l>
                        <l>That he's a Slave, nor that ought him beſots,</l>
                        <l>Although he place his happineſs in Drink:</l>
                        <l>O how his heart doth long, and thirſt, and pine,</l>
                        <l>E'r to be drinking, quaffing Beer or Wine!</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="90">
                        <head>[90.]</head>
                        <l>He loves good Fellows, Pot-companions dear,</l>
                        <l>His Life and Joy lies in that Fellowſhip,</l>
                        <l>Th'are farre more priz'd by him than all Heavens Queer.</l>
                        <l>Than Living Waters he had rather ſip</l>
                        <l>His luniſh Cups of Soul-confounding Drink,</l>
                        <l>Though thereby Health, Eſtate, Soul, Body ſinck.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="91">
                        <head>[91.]</head>
                        <l>Tuſh, tell not him of the Tribunal Day,</l>
                        <l>Nor of <hi>Jehovah</hi>'s dreadfull flaming ire;</l>
                        <l>Come give him Drink to waſh dry cares away;</l>
                        <l>He fears no Hell, he fears no flames of fire;</l>
                        <l>Thus doth his throat already him foretell</l>
                        <l>His Souls Diſeaſe for evermore in Hell.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="92">
                        <head>[92.]</head>
                        <l>And are proud Wantons any whit leſs Fools?</l>
                        <l>Their task's as hard, and yet that task is ſweet</l>
                        <l>Unto them, the heat of their deſire what cools?</l>
                        <l>Thoughts of Eternity muſt not them greet:</l>
                        <l>Bid them be humble, holy, chaſte, and pure,</l>
                        <l>Such clowniſh Precepts they cannot endure.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="93">
                        <pb n="35" facs="tcp:170222:24"/>
                        <head>[93.]</head>
                        <l>But why ſtand I thus for to inſtance any</l>
                        <l>One ſingle Vice, when all the Ills of Nature</l>
                        <l>Do prove the ſame moſt clearly? though not many</l>
                        <l>Take notice of it, active in each feature</l>
                        <l>The moſt of men hotly perſiſt to do,</l>
                        <l>What ere their wieldy Paſſions lead them to.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="94">
                        <head>[94.]</head>
                        <l>Well to conclude young man; Remember this,</l>
                        <l>Thy Soul's immortal, and muſt aye endure,</l>
                        <l>'Twas made by God a Subject fit for Bliſs,</l>
                        <l>And of eternal Doom it muſt be ſure.</l>
                        <l>If thou liv'ſt well, a Crown he'l to thee give;</l>
                        <l>If ill, thy Doom's with Devils for to live.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="95">
                        <head>[95.]</head>
                        <l>But having been too tedious in my verſe</l>
                        <l>Upon this ſubject Pleaſure, (and yet I</l>
                        <l>Have been but brief and ſhort, ſeeing commerce</l>
                        <l>By youth is held with Pleaſure conſtantly)</l>
                        <l>Shall now for Recreation ſake expreſs</l>
                        <l>In varied Verſe what my experience is.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="96">
                        <head>[96.]</head>
                        <l>And what in mine own practice I do act</l>
                        <l>Of youthfull pleaſure, how I it eſteem,</l>
                        <l>I ſhall lay down my thoughts of many a Fact</l>
                        <l>Tending thereto, and what I of it deem.</l>
                        <l>Example is a living Argument,</l>
                        <l>My ſelf to thee, as ſo I here preſent.</l>
                        <pb n="36" facs="tcp:170222:25"/>
                        <l>Pleaſure I finde to be a ſly,</l>
                        <l>A deadly, ſubtil Enemy,</l>
                        <l>'Twill ſleer i' th' face, 'twill kiſs the lip,</l>
                        <l>Yet then look to 't, 'twill up thee trip;</l>
                        <l>'Twill ſpeak thee fair, 'twill kindly greet,</l>
                        <l>And ſtraight 'twill lay thee at its feet;</l>
                        <l>'Twill promiſe thee large liberty,</l>
                        <l>(When nothing's a more real Lie;)</l>
                        <l>'Twill build thee Caſtles in th' air,</l>
                        <l>'Twill fawn, and lie, and ſpeak thee fair,</l>
                        <l>'Twill mention Peace, that it will give thee,</l>
                        <l>But truſt it not, it will deceive thee;</l>
                        <l>'Twill 'ford content and ſatisfaction,</l>
                        <l>But then 't muſt be in Soul-diſtraction;</l>
                        <l>'Twill promiſe Ells, perform no Inch;</l>
                        <l>Thou needſt not queſtion at a pinch</l>
                        <l>But it will help thee unto ſorrow,</l>
                        <l>Deep-dy'd in grain, and Scarlet-horrour;</l>
                        <l>'Twill proffer thee its company,</l>
                        <l>And promiſe true fidelity;</l>
                        <l>Faithfull 'twill be (indeed) 't w'on't leave thee</l>
                        <l>Herein, I ſay, it w'on't deceive thee,</l>
                        <l>'Twill ſtick cloſe to thee to bereave thee</l>
                        <l>Of what ere Heaven, or God can give thee;</l>
                        <l>'Twill lodg thee with it ſelf in Hell,</l>
                        <l>Together live and die (all's well;)</l>
                        <l>'Tis ſweet in ſhew, but proves moſt ſowre,</l>
                        <l>Shews lovely fair, but yet will lowre;</l>
                        <l>It ſays, in it thou ſhalt enjoy</l>
                        <l>Such matter as ſhall ne're thee cloy:</l>
                        <pb n="37" facs="tcp:170222:25"/>
                        <l>'Tis partly truth, for parting never</l>
                        <l>Is living and enjoying ever,</l>
                        <l>Which thou, and it, and Hell ſha'n't do,</l>
                        <l>When once conjoyned thereunto:</l>
                        <l>O therefore now betimes reſolve</l>
                        <l>That knot of Friendſhip to diſſolve,</l>
                        <l>When ere ſhe doth herſelf preſent</l>
                        <l>(I need not queſtion her intent,</l>
                        <l>I know her well, though ſhe doth bring</l>
                        <l>Honey in mouth, her tail doth ſting)</l>
                        <l>To me, I ask what ſhe doth crave?</l>
                        <l>Or what 'tis of me ſhe would have?</l>
                        <l>I ask, how long I ſhall be ſure</l>
                        <l>What ſhe can give me will endure?</l>
                        <l>(Before I leap I love to look,</l>
                        <l>But all ſuch counſel cannot brook)</l>
                        <l>Shall this thy joy continue ever?</l>
                        <l>And ſhall its life expire never?</l>
                        <l>Say I to her, Will this thy Pleaſure</l>
                        <l>Not dammage my eternal Treaſure?</l>
                        <l>If 't be n't eternal, then be gone,</l>
                        <l>Entice me not, let me alone;</l>
                        <l>'Tis no fit object for my view,</l>
                        <l>An unfit ſubject to purſue,</l>
                        <l>To gain thoſe things I will perſever,</l>
                        <l>That (like my Soul) endure for ever,</l>
                        <l>I dare not give thee any room,</l>
                        <l>Becauſe to judgment I muſt come;</l>
                        <l>I know the Judg and thou art Foes,</l>
                        <l>If thee I follow, him I loſe.</l>
                        <pb n="38" facs="tcp:170222:26"/>
                        <l>Avaunt, Be gone, Stand off; therefore</l>
                        <l>Don't dare (bold Sin) to tempt me more:</l>
                        <l>My heart thy dainties doth diſrelliſh,</l>
                        <l>Becauſe deceit doth them embelliſh:</l>
                        <l>Such Evils (too) they tend to cheriſh,</l>
                        <l>As will make Soul and Body periſh;</l>
                        <l>Thy pleaſant Path doth lead to Hell,</l>
                        <l>With damned ſpirits for to dwell;</l>
                        <l>Mine eys therefore thereon ſha'n't look,</l>
                        <l>To hear thereof mine ears ſha'n't brook,</l>
                        <l>Unto thy Paths my feet ſha'n't walk</l>
                        <l>Nor of thee ſhall not my tongue talk:</l>
                        <l>All thoughts of thee, O may I ſmother,</l>
                        <l>Who am the intereſt of another:</l>
                        <l>Diſloyall am I him unto,</l>
                        <l>If I ſtrike friendſhip with his Foe,</l>
                        <l>I dare not, O, I dare not I,</l>
                        <l>Think ſuch a thought, for he ſtands by,</l>
                        <l>He hath a Cabbin in my Breaſt,</l>
                        <l>He knows what's not by me expreſt,</l>
                        <l>His eye doth every ſecret ſee,</l>
                        <l>Kept ignorant he cannot be,</l>
                        <l>He's omni-preſent, filleth all</l>
                        <l>And every place both great and ſmall;</l>
                        <l>His arm is long, he will me reach,</l>
                        <l>From Eaſt to Weſt the ſame doth ſtretch,</l>
                        <l>How then dare I conſent to ſin,</l>
                        <l>Or any one thought harbour in</l>
                        <l>My tender breaſt, that may conduce</l>
                        <l>His ſacred Name to prejudice;</l>
                        <pb n="39" facs="tcp:170222:26"/>
                        <l>He's juſt and jealous, I don't dare</l>
                        <l>Him to offend, my Soul doth fear</l>
                        <l>His righteous judgments, and my fleſh</l>
                        <l>Doth tremble, and can do no leſs:</l>
                        <l>His Majeſty, in flames of fire</l>
                        <l>Cloath'd with wrath and furious ire,</l>
                        <l>Shall make appearance when the world</l>
                        <l>By fiery flames ſhall be diſſolv'd,</l>
                        <l>Shall mount upon his glorious Throne,</l>
                        <l>And then examine every one;</l>
                        <l>All acts muſt into judgment come,</l>
                        <l>And every one receive their Doom,</l>
                        <l>According to their ſeveral Deeds,</l>
                        <l>The Judg to them their Sentence reades,</l>
                        <l>He ſays to them that have done well,</l>
                        <l>Ye bleſſed of my Father dwell</l>
                        <l>In his bright glories, mount the Throne</l>
                        <l>Prepared for ye every one;</l>
                        <l>Ye did your hearts for me maintain,</l>
                        <l>Come therefore now and with me reign;</l>
                        <l>Ye on the earth did to me live,</l>
                        <l>Now I to you a Kingdom give;</l>
                        <l>You hated Sin, now I you own,</l>
                        <l>And give you an all-glorious Crown;</l>
                        <l>You of your ways did conſcience make,</l>
                        <l>Your wills and luſts too (for my ſake)</l>
                        <l>Did crucifie, with ſtrength oppoſe</l>
                        <l>All the ſuggeſtions of my foes;</l>
                        <l>Your ſtrength up to me you did give,</l>
                        <l>Come therefore your Reward receive.</l>
                        <pb n="40" facs="tcp:170222:27"/>
                        <l>But as for you, you helliſh Elves,</l>
                        <l>That to your Luſts did give your ſelves,</l>
                        <l>That ever burn'd with ſtrong deſire,</l>
                        <l>Bred and maintain'd by wanton fire;</l>
                        <l>Be gone from me into thoſe flames,</l>
                        <l>That burn and nought their fury tames,</l>
                        <l>As in your life-time you have been</l>
                        <l>A neer Aſſociate to Sin,</l>
                        <l>So now therewith go bide and dwell</l>
                        <l>For ever in the loweſt Hell,</l>
                        <l>In utter darkneſs make abode,</l>
                        <l>Under my flaming furious Rod,</l>
                        <l>There live out your eternal breath,</l>
                        <l>With howling cries, with gnaſhing teeth,</l>
                        <l>I know right well this is Sins Doom,</l>
                        <l>Therefore I dare not giue it room,</l>
                        <l>I dare not entertain it in me,</l>
                        <l>For ſure I am it ſoon will win me,</l>
                        <l>Its joy doth but a moment laſt,</l>
                        <l>But ah! its pain is never paſt,</l>
                        <l>Eternity my Soul doth eye,</l>
                        <l>Vain Pleaſure therefore dare not I</l>
                        <l>Once look upon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor will I greet</l>
                        <l>It, whereſoever I it meet:</l>
                        <l>I know it is an helliſh Fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nd,</l>
                        <l>And all its courſes thither tend.</l>
                        <l>Be gone, be gone, thou doſt beguile me,</l>
                        <l>And of moſt pleaſant ſweets doſt ſpoil me,</l>
                        <l>Thou giv'ſt me Peebles for my Treaſures,</l>
                        <l>Sharp ſorrows for delightfull Pleaſures:</l>
                        <pb n="41" facs="tcp:170222:27"/>
                        <l>Mine own I am not, but am bought</l>
                        <l>At a dear rate, and therefore ought</l>
                        <l>To give both Soul and Body too</l>
                        <l>Unto his bleſſed ſervice, who</l>
                        <l>Did me redeem from bondage fell,</l>
                        <l>Reprieve my Soul from Death and Hell;</l>
                        <l>He gave his Life, his Love was ſuch,</l>
                        <l>To men, and ſhall I then think much</l>
                        <l>To anſwer love with love entire,</l>
                        <l>And for his ſake to quench the fire</l>
                        <l>Of lower loves, and with affection</l>
                        <l>Moſt pure and true, yeeld him ſubjection;</l>
                        <l>Long may I to him loyal prove,</l>
                        <l>Strong may I with him be in love;</l>
                        <l>The pleaſures of religion I,</l>
                        <l>Do finde more ſweet and do eſpye</l>
                        <l>More beauty in, than want on pleaſure</l>
                        <l>Can give to them, that have moſt leiſure</l>
                        <l>To wait thereon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in it I finde</l>
                        <l>That ſweet repoſe unto my minde,</l>
                        <l>That peace, that ſweet delight, that joy,</l>
                        <l>That worldly powers cann't deſtroy:</l>
                        <l>Faith feeds me with the Bread of Heaven;</l>
                        <l>Thereby to me its joys are given</l>
                        <l>In ſuch a meaſure that oft I</l>
                        <l>Being overcharg'd with joy do cry,</l>
                        <l>(As of my ſenſes quite bereaven)</l>
                        <l>Whether am I now in Earth or Heaven?</l>
                        <l>What's this I both feel, taſte and ſee?</l>
                        <l>Sure I am in Heaven, or Heaven's in me.</l>
                        <pb n="42" facs="tcp:170222:28"/>
                        <l>Time ſlackes his courſe, his glaſs do'n't run,</l>
                        <l>Or is eternity begun?</l>
                        <l>Both weeks and months their motions ſtay,</l>
                        <l>They are to me as one ſhort day;</l>
                        <l>But they that would of Soul delight</l>
                        <l>(Then this) have a more fuller ſight</l>
                        <l>From me, then let them pleaſe to look</l>
                        <l>Upon another former book;</l>
                        <l>I penn'd (in part) long ſince, and there</l>
                        <l>Expreſſions make 't at large appeare.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="97">
                        <head>[97.]</head>
                        <l>But ſtill for to purſue my preſent task,</l>
                        <l>As youthfull blood doth make the wind aſpire</l>
                        <l>To fading honour, after pleaſure ask,</l>
                        <l>Setting the Senſes thereon all on fire;</l>
                        <l>So too that heated blood the Soul doth move,</l>
                        <l>To be a thralled Captive unto Love.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="98">
                        <head>[98.]</head>
                        <l>Youth's ſwelling veines made hot with blood and Spirits,</l>
                        <l>Doth like to fire never ceaſe to ſtur:</l>
                        <l>Will be in motion, though thereby 't inherits,</l>
                        <l>Shame for the ſame a conſtant blur,</l>
                        <l>The Soul of man is made of living fire,</l>
                        <l>That never moves yet motion don't expire.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="99">
                        <head>[99.]</head>
                        <l>The Devill therefore tends with diligence,</l>
                        <l>To give it matter whereupon to act:</l>
                        <l>Preſents an object to the greedy Senſe,</l>
                        <l>The which from thence the Soul doth ſoon infect,</l>
                        <l>Unto the Eye of youth he proffers beauty,</l>
                        <l>And ſtreight fond youth preſents it ſhrine with duty.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="100">
                        <pb n="43" facs="tcp:170222:28"/>
                        <head>[100.]</head>
                        <l>Beauty to youth is as the oyle 't a fire,</l>
                        <l>And as dry fewel unto raging flames</l>
                        <l>It doth convert him all into deſire,</l>
                        <l>And what is 't then that furious paſſion tames;</l>
                        <l>Th' eye to the heart preſents this foul infection,</l>
                        <l>Poyſons the Soul thoroughout, by the affection.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="101">
                        <head>[101.]</head>
                        <l>Youth now doth love, and muſt poſſeſſe in love</l>
                        <l>What he deſires, on whom his heart is fixt;</l>
                        <l>All arguments are far too weak to move,</l>
                        <l>There is no incongruity betwixt</l>
                        <l>Her whom he loves and him; no he can tell</l>
                        <l>She ſuits his diſpoſition very well.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="102">
                        <head>[102.]</head>
                        <l>What will he ſtick to venture for her ſake,</l>
                        <l>Whom he ſo fondly loves, as that his life</l>
                        <l>I' n't deare unto him, ſo he may partake</l>
                        <l>Her fellowſhip, and ſhe be made his wife;</l>
                        <l>Heaven and earth and God and life and bliſſe,</l>
                        <l>Compar'd with her unto him norhing is.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Youths antick tricks herein I ſha'n't diſcover,</l>
                        <l>I do'n't intend to toile my muſe ſo much:</l>
                        <l>Again my Soul thereof was ne'r a lover,</l>
                        <l>And therefore once to ſpeak of them I grutch;</l>
                        <l>My Soul takes no delight ſuch things to mention,</l>
                        <l>Further than is concern'd in my intention.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="104">
                        <pb n="44" facs="tcp:170222:29"/>
                        <head>[104.]</head>
                        <l>Is thy blood hot? (youth) do thy Spirits move,</l>
                        <l>And work thee to a flame of ſtrong deſire?</l>
                        <l>Make God the onely object of thy love,</l>
                        <l>Preſent him with an heart ſound and entire;</l>
                        <l>He's the alone-original of beauty,</l>
                        <l>His lovelineſſe (from thee) may win a duty.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="105">
                        <head>[105.]</head>
                        <l>If thou could'ſt ſee him with a ſingle eye</l>
                        <l>His lovely beauty, but by glance behold:</l>
                        <l>I'm ſure in him thy Soul would ſoon eſpye,</l>
                        <l>That which would make thy burning love grow cold</l>
                        <l>To all things elſe, and all things diſappeare,</l>
                        <l>In lovelineſſe to what before me were.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="106">
                        <head>[106.]</head>
                        <l>Thoſe ſparkling glories, whoſe unmatchleſs luſtre</l>
                        <l>Do make a heaven where e'r they are unfolded,</l>
                        <l>Diſplayed to thy view thy thoughts would muſter,</l>
                        <l>And ſet them free from what they are inthralled;</l>
                        <l>'Twould flame thy Spirits, and thou then ſhould'ſt prove,</l>
                        <l>The power of that noble heaven-bred love.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="107">
                        <head>[107.]</head>
                        <l>Love of this beauty don't the Soul abaſe,</l>
                        <l>Nor make it act below it ſelf as t' other:</l>
                        <l>Which doth ignoble it, and much deface</l>
                        <l>Its beauties, tending alſo for to ſmother</l>
                        <l>All ſparks of good, that are contain'd therein,</l>
                        <l>By the baſe ſmoaky vapours of foul Sin.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="108">
                        <pb n="45" facs="tcp:170222:29"/>
                        <head>[108.]</head>
                        <l>No this doth raiſe and elevate the mind,</l>
                        <l>And doth ennoble, and ſublime the Soul:</l>
                        <l>It makes it unto real good enclin'd,</l>
                        <l>Refines and purges it from courſes foul;</l>
                        <l>It doth tranſmute, transform and make the Spirit</l>
                        <l>From real ill true goodneſs to enherit.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="109">
                        <head>[109.]</head>
                        <l>This love to God doth ſpread it ſelf throughout</l>
                        <l>The inner man, and ſtrange effects it worketh:</l>
                        <l>It doth employ its utmoſt ſtrength about</l>
                        <l>Ejecting Sin from whence it cloſely lurketh;</l>
                        <l>Oh, here's delight indeed! the Soul doth move,</l>
                        <l>Employed in the ſervice of its love.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="110">
                        <head>[110.]</head>
                        <l>Lovers oft beg this on their bended knee,</l>
                        <l>(O great abaſement of a noble Soul!)</l>
                        <l>That by their miſtris they employ'd may bee,</l>
                        <l>The ſervice ne'r ſo baſe, low, mean or foul;</l>
                        <l>O for her ſake what wo'n't they deign to do,</l>
                        <l>They'll bended bow even for to kiſſe her Shooe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="111">
                        <head>[111.]</head>
                        <l>Loves Nature 'tis to act with joy and cheere,</l>
                        <l>In any act whereto their Love enjoynes'm:</l>
                        <l>Love's life therein conſiſts, and doth appear</l>
                        <l>'Tis love, and love't ſelf thereof doth mind'm;</l>
                        <l>Then Chriſtians who are happyer men than you,</l>
                        <l>That ever have advantages enow</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="112">
                        <pb n="46" facs="tcp:170222:30"/>
                        <head>[112.]</head>
                        <l>To prove and to expreſſe your love to him,</l>
                        <l>The fountaine of all love, the King of glory:</l>
                        <l>Unto whoſe ſhine Sol's ſplendent rayes are dim,</l>
                        <l>Whoſe beauty Seraphims't would poſe to ſtory;</l>
                        <l>By mortifying Sin, by crucifying</l>
                        <l>All earthly members, to ſelf-wiſdome dying.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="113">
                        <head>[113.]</head>
                        <l>Oh! 'tis advantage Chriſtians to be tempted,</l>
                        <l>By ſordid humours, by a baſe deſire;</l>
                        <l>For why; thereby occaſion is preſented,</l>
                        <l>To purge your Soules and prove your love entire;</l>
                        <l>Sin tempts, the Soul oppoſes, God looks on</l>
                        <l>As the Spectator, to behold what's done.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="114">
                        <head>[114.]</head>
                        <l>O how thou'dſt fight young man, if that a foe</l>
                        <l>Of thy beloveds did encounter with thee;</l>
                        <l>Eſpecially if ſhe commanded ſo,</l>
                        <l>And did looke on herſelf; but then I prethee</l>
                        <l>Tell me, doſt think ſervice to the creator</l>
                        <l>Affords leſſe joy than ſervice to the creature?</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="115">
                        <head>[115.]</head>
                        <l>How happy do your lovers think themſelves,</l>
                        <l>If they may bee but graced for to talk</l>
                        <l>With their deare love: Oh! how the minde now delves</l>
                        <l>For matter, there's no faculty doth balk,</l>
                        <l>Its utmoſt ſtrength for to give up in this,</l>
                        <l>In this ſame act wherein conſiſts its Blis,</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="116">
                        <pb n="47" facs="tcp:170222:30"/>
                        <head>[116.]</head>
                        <l>Words from her mouth you prize as hony dewes,</l>
                        <l>Yea Nectar, &amp; Ambroſia a'n't ſo ſweet</l>
                        <l>As her diſcourſe is to you; while her brows</l>
                        <l>Diſplayed in lovely ſmiles deigns you to greet;</l>
                        <l>Her words drop down like Manna from the Skies,</l>
                        <l>While with delights ye bathe ye in her eys.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="117">
                        <head>[117.]</head>
                        <l>O happy ye, your hearts now melt in love,</l>
                        <l>And like to Wax before the Sun diſſolveth,</l>
                        <l>Ye now lie captivated, cannot move</l>
                        <l>Untill ſhe from this bondage you abſolveth;</l>
                        <l>You bath your ſouls in this her ſunny-ſhine,</l>
                        <l>And think her favours more than half divine.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="118">
                        <head>[118.]</head>
                        <l>But what's all this to thoſe unmatchleſs favours,</l>
                        <l>That they who ſeek the face of God do meet?</l>
                        <l>The very way and path they tread in, ſavours</l>
                        <l>Of joys illuſtrious, moſt delightfull ſweet,</l>
                        <l>Where ere he moves the ſweets he leaves behinde him</l>
                        <l>Is a ſufficient tract whereby to finde him.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="119">
                        <head>[119.]</head>
                        <l>They that love him he turns them love again,</l>
                        <l>And who with diligence his face do ſeek</l>
                        <l>His glorious face ſhall ſee (to quit their pain)</l>
                        <l>(Under a veil) yet lovely, ſweet and meek;</l>
                        <l>O could I tell what his imperial brow</l>
                        <l>Affords to them that ſee't, 'twould raviſh you.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="120">
                        <pb n="48" facs="tcp:170222:31"/>
                        <head>[120.]</head>
                        <l>So lively glorious, ſo ſweet, ſo cleare,</l>
                        <l>So Sp'ritly vigorous, and Soul-reviving,</l>
                        <l>So milde, ſo gentle, yet ſo lovely faire,</l>
                        <l>The Soul that ſees it, ceaſes e'r from dying;</l>
                        <l>I cannot half conceive, much leſſe expreſſe</l>
                        <l>The joy, the bleſſedneſſe that therein is.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="121">
                        <head>[121.]</head>
                        <l>Converſe with him; yea freely that you may,</l>
                        <l>He'l find you matter fit for to converſe on;</l>
                        <l>Nay, further He'l you ſend a glorious ray,</l>
                        <l>To fit your hearts for what they do commerce on;</l>
                        <l>Here's love indeed your Love, this thing can't do,</l>
                        <l>If you'r infirm, ſhe throws a ſcorne on you.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="122">
                        <head>[122.]</head>
                        <l>He ſends his Spirit to renue dead flames,</l>
                        <l>To quicken, to revive th' affection dying:</l>
                        <l>A God of grace and love, himſelf he names,</l>
                        <l>His Nature's ſo; his Soul is ever eying</l>
                        <l>His creatures wants, the languiſhing deſire</l>
                        <l>He cheriſhes with Grace, doth re-enſpire.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="123">
                        <head>[123.]</head>
                        <l>How ſweet ſo-e're your thoughts are when you muſe,</l>
                        <l>Upon your Miſtreſſes moſt lovely face,</l>
                        <l>Her perſon and proportion, when refuſe</l>
                        <l>You do that any thoughts them ſhould diſplace;</l>
                        <l>Yet know ev'n then the thoughts of God are ſweeter,</l>
                        <l>His love more lovelyer, his Spirit fleeter.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="124">
                        <pb n="49" facs="tcp:170222:31"/>
                        <head>[124.]</head>
                        <l>Being wounded by the beauty of her face,</l>
                        <l>Her words have power to kill or give you life:</l>
                        <l>Your Soules do ſue for to obtain her grace,</l>
                        <l>To gain her love, that ſhee'd be made your wife;</l>
                        <l>When ſhe is pleas'd to greet you with diſdain,</l>
                        <l>Your Spirit ſinkes, no life in't doth remain.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="125">
                        <head>[125.]</head>
                        <l>But this to great <hi>Jehovahs</hi> powerfull voyce,</l>
                        <l>Which is Soul quickning, or Soul confounding:</l>
                        <l>Wilt thou joyn paralell to make a choyce,</l>
                        <l>('Tween real want and what is moſt abounding?)</l>
                        <l>His voice ſuch rare magnetique power doth give;</l>
                        <l>'T preſerves the dying, makes the dead to live.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="126">
                        <head>[126.]</head>
                        <l>Touch'd with his beames, touch'd with his flames of love,</l>
                        <l>An extaſy that Soul muſt needs remain in,</l>
                        <l>'Tis bounden to him, and it cannot move,</l>
                        <l>That bed' maines ever green that it hath lyen in;</l>
                        <l>Oh, ſtop my laviſh pen, I cann't tell how,</l>
                        <l>Thoſe rare unmatchleſſe ſweets <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>'deſcribe to you.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="127">
                        <head>[127.]</head>
                        <l>Youth, canſt thou dote on any female beauty,</l>
                        <l>What doſt thou think thou ſhalt therein enjoy?</l>
                        <l>That thou doſt vow thereto ſuch ſolemn duty,</l>
                        <l>Demean thy ſelf ſo like a witleſſe boy;</l>
                        <l>By any antick geſtures her to gain,</l>
                        <l>Whom being got thou doſt poſſeſſe with pain,</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="128">
                        <pb n="50" facs="tcp:170222:32"/>
                        <head>[128.]</head>
                        <l>Alas, thou over-prize<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> things a far,</l>
                        <l>And buy'ſt th' enjoyments at a rate too dear,</l>
                        <l>'Tis granted in their place they ſomething are</l>
                        <l>But what; ('tis not my task to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ell you here;)</l>
                        <l>Yet minde yee what <hi>Elchanah</hi> ſay'd to <hi>Hanny,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Am not I more to thee than children many?</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="129">
                        <head>[129.]</head>
                        <l>So in <hi>Jehove</hi> is far more to be found,</l>
                        <l>Than in all Creatures if conjoyn'd together:</l>
                        <l>All creature-ſweet is in a moment drown'd</l>
                        <l>In thoſe delights that he affordeth, whither</l>
                        <l>The Soul at all times freely may reſort,</l>
                        <l>And with thoſe pleaſures may it ſelf diſport.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="130">
                        <head>[130.]</head>
                        <l>Pleaſures, ſweet pleaſures, precious delights,</l>
                        <l>To theſe expreſſions youngling ſure I ſee thee</l>
                        <l>Attend and bend thine ear, (come nought affrights)</l>
                        <l>Be ſober and let thoſe expreſſions chear thee;</l>
                        <l>God is the riſt of beauty, peace and love,</l>
                        <l>Joy and delight, and therefore to him move.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="131">
                        <head>[131.]</head>
                        <l>As from a mighty fountain that diſperſes</l>
                        <l>Its great aboundance thorough many ſprings,</l>
                        <l>And in thoſe narrow channels quickly paſſes,</l>
                        <l>And ſpreads its ſelf and waters divers things;</l>
                        <l>So doth <hi>Jehove</hi> from his own fullneſs give</l>
                        <l>What ever good the creature can receive.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="132">
                        <pb n="51" facs="tcp:170222:32"/>
                        <head>[132.]</head>
                        <l>Now 'tis abſurd to think, much more to ſay,</l>
                        <l>That there reſides that fullneſs in one Spring</l>
                        <l>That in the fountain head it ſelf doth ſtay,</l>
                        <l>No more can any creature comfort bring</l>
                        <l>That peace, joy, Satisfaction to the mind,</l>
                        <l>That in <hi>Jehove</hi> himſelf thy Soul may find.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="133">
                        <head>[133.]</head>
                        <l>Extract what ere thou canſt from ev'ry creature,</l>
                        <l>And pack that lovelyneſſe all up in one;</l>
                        <l>Beauty from one and from another feature,</l>
                        <l>(Perfection reſteth not in one alone,)</l>
                        <l>From a third virtue, a well compoſed Spirit,</l>
                        <l>That ſweetneſſe, patience, mildneſſe doth enherit,</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="134">
                        <head>[134.]</head>
                        <l>Nay take the Quinteſſence of ev'ry thing</l>
                        <l>That thou in any creature good canſt call,</l>
                        <l>And then know this that all that good doth ſpring,</l>
                        <l>From God its fount and its original;</l>
                        <l>And if one ſingle good ſo lovely is,</l>
                        <l>What's he in whom thou maiſt them all poſſeſſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="135">
                        <head>[135.]</head>
                        <l>Note this young man, and deep impreſſion give it</l>
                        <l>Upon thine heart, endorſe it on thy mind:</l>
                        <l>Upon thy judgment do it faſt on rivet,</l>
                        <l>And let it equal entertainment find</l>
                        <l>To things of far leſſe worth, inferiour beauty,</l>
                        <l>Remove from that, and give to this that duty.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="136">
                        <pb n="52" facs="tcp:170222:33"/>
                        <head>[136.]</head>
                        <l>Thou canſt not ſay that this is a demand,</l>
                        <l>Unreaſonable of thee to be ask'd?</l>
                        <l>The worth of th'object rightly underſtand,</l>
                        <l>And then thou'lt not complain that thou art task'd,</l>
                        <l>In any ſervice that thou undertak'ſt</l>
                        <l>For it to do, nor that deer thou forſak'ſt</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="137">
                        <head>[137.]</head>
                        <l>It for to gain, cauſe worth far leſs doth move</l>
                        <l>Thee, coſt, labour and ſtrength for to lay out,</l>
                        <l>To be an humble ſervant in her love,</l>
                        <l>And think't a bliſs to be employ'd about</l>
                        <l>(At any time) the ſervice of her pleaſure,</l>
                        <l>Which to fullfill, thou ſpareſt for no treaſure.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="138">
                        <head>[138.]</head>
                        <l>And all's to gain what may be loſt to morrow,</l>
                        <l>But if not ſo, yet's but a petty good,</l>
                        <l>A ſweet that doth contain a deal of ſorrow,</l>
                        <l>A peace that many diſcontentments hood.</l>
                        <l>Leave not the kernel for the empty ſhell,</l>
                        <l>When as thou mayſt enjoy'm both aſwell.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="139">
                        <head>[139.]</head>
                        <l>But to look ore thoſe petty petty ſweets,</l>
                        <l>That thou endeareſt to thee as thy life:</l>
                        <l>And for to mention ſome of many feates,</l>
                        <l>That in thy nature's acted very rife;</l>
                        <l>Thou ne'r doſt leave till thou haſt found an object,</l>
                        <l>Whereto thou makeſt thine affections ſubject.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="140">
                        <pb n="53" facs="tcp:170222:33"/>
                        <head>[140.]</head>
                        <l>Oh! might thy active thoughts employ themſelves</l>
                        <l>No leſſe in ſeeking out to find abode,</l>
                        <l>'Cquaintance and friendſhip and him that e'r dwels,</l>
                        <l>Between the Cherubims, thy heaven, thy God;</l>
                        <l>Thy ſelf caſt down before him, proſtrate ly</l>
                        <l>With reſolution, if I dy, I dy.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="141">
                        <head>[141.]</head>
                        <l>This thou wilt do to gain her worthleſſe favour,</l>
                        <l>On whom thou doſt thy fond affection pitch:</l>
                        <l>There is no good like that, that thou canſt favour,</l>
                        <l>Nor any thing that thou eſteem'ſt ſo much;</l>
                        <l>Therefore thou layſt out all thy Art and ſtrength,</l>
                        <l>With ſtrong deſire, her to enjoy at length.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="142">
                        <head>[142.]</head>
                        <l>The Suns bright rayes do far leſs comfort yeild,</l>
                        <l>Then doth the ſunny beauty of her face;</l>
                        <l>To which thou thinkeſt that the fragrant field</l>
                        <l>Is leſſe delightfull, nor of ſo much grace.</l>
                        <l>There is no happineſs thou canſt eſpy,</l>
                        <l>Out of the ſun-ſhine of thy Miſtris's eye:</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="143">
                        <head>[143.]</head>
                        <l>Thy life and happineſſe lies in her ſmiles,</l>
                        <l>Thy death and miſery in her frown conſiſteth,</l>
                        <l>Thy fond affection thus thy judgment ſpoiles,</l>
                        <l>Will and deſire do in thee what them liſteth;</l>
                        <l>Affection, will, and vain deſire together</l>
                        <l>Do lead th'enthraled judgment any whither.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="144">
                        <pb n="54" facs="tcp:170222:34"/>
                        <head>[144.]</head>
                        <l>But oh fond youth that thou could'ſt turn about,</l>
                        <l>And ſee that worth from which thou turn'ſt thy face,</l>
                        <l>Ah! did'ſt thou but behold it, out of doubt</l>
                        <l>Thou would'ſt endeavour for to give it place;</l>
                        <l>Tis worth where from th'algorious Queere of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</l>
                        <l>Have all their happineſſe unto them given.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="145">
                        <head>[145.]</head>
                        <l>Tis worth affording each Soul faculty,</l>
                        <l>A full contentment of all needful things:</l>
                        <l>A real worth where's no deceit, no ly,</l>
                        <l>Perfect delight and joy that's free from ſtings;</l>
                        <l>'Tis more then th' Quinteſſence of every good,</l>
                        <l>It is a worth that can't be underſtood.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="146">
                        <head>[146.]</head>
                        <l>It is a worth from whenceall worth's derived,</l>
                        <l>'Tis real ſubſtance, thine a vain conceit:</l>
                        <l>'Tis death eternal for to be deprived</l>
                        <l>Sight of the face of that al-glorious wight;</l>
                        <l>'Tis life e'rlaſting it for to enjoy,</l>
                        <l>Where's all delight and peace without annoy.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="147">
                        <head>[147.]</head>
                        <l>A dark and loathſome Dungeon is that place,</l>
                        <l>(Of no delight, but ſorrow now to thee?)</l>
                        <l>That thy dear Loves ſweet preſence us'd to grace,</l>
                        <l>Where thou her lovely-face did'ſt uſe to ſee;</l>
                        <l>Her ſunny beauty was that place's light</l>
                        <l>To thee, her abſence mak'ſt a darkſome night.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="148">
                        <pb n="55" facs="tcp:170222:34"/>
                        <head>[148.]</head>
                        <l>This thou experienceſt and knowſt it truth,</l>
                        <l>But in the Suuny beauty of Gods eye</l>
                        <l>(Regardleſſe, negligent, vain, witleſſe youth,)</l>
                        <l>Thou knowſt not what an happineſſe doth ly;</l>
                        <l>For 'tis his face, his preſence that makes Heaven,</l>
                        <l>Who ſees it not of all joys are bereaven.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="149">
                        <head>[149.]</head>
                        <l>Ah! couldſt but half conſider what it is,</l>
                        <l>To live without him, be depriv'd the place</l>
                        <l>Of his abode, the miſery to miſs</l>
                        <l>The ſight of his beſt ſmiles, his lovely grace;</l>
                        <l>'T would break thy heart to think upon that ſorrow,</l>
                        <l>(That thou muſt feele thereby) with deadly horrour.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="150">
                        <head>[150.]</head>
                        <l>The loſſe of any creature Love i'n't ſo,</l>
                        <l>That loſſe may in an other be repaired:</l>
                        <l>Beare but the grief, no puniſhment may go</l>
                        <l>Along therewith beſide, that may be ſpared;</l>
                        <l>Conſidering (for ought thou know'ſt) that loſſe,</l>
                        <l>It had by thee might 'ave prov'd a cruel croſſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="151">
                        <head>[151.]</head>
                        <l>For why on earth no ſweet's without ſome ſowre,</l>
                        <l>There is no peace without ſome diſcontentment,</l>
                        <l>Withoutſome weakneſs there's no ſtrength, no power</l>
                        <l>No earth without ſome grief can't make preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</l>
                        <l>Of any joy unto thee in the leaſt,</l>
                        <l>At its vain Loves let not thy ſoul (then) feaſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="152">
                        <pb n="56" facs="tcp:170222:35"/>
                        <head>[152.]</head>
                        <l>But leaſt ſome perſons ſhould exceptions take,</l>
                        <l>(By miſinterpreting my aime, my drift)</l>
                        <l>And ſay Gods ordinance I uſeleſſe make,</l>
                        <l>And chaſtity is a peculiar gift;</l>
                        <l>I wiſh ſuch perſons rightly to conceive me;</l>
                        <l>I aime at no ſuch thing, if they'll beleeve me.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="153">
                        <head>[153.]</head>
                        <l>I don't condemn ſuch Love as lawfull is,</l>
                        <l>But fain would lead the creature a pitch higher,</l>
                        <l>Above all firſt to ſeek eternal bliſſe,</l>
                        <l>To God himſelf would have the Soul aſpire;</l>
                        <l>Would have it firſt to mind the things of heaven,</l>
                        <l>Then all things elſe ſhall be (as vantage) given.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="154">
                        <head>[154.]</head>
                        <l>I'd have youth give the prime of their affection,</l>
                        <l>As their firſt fruit unto <hi>Jehovah</hi> due,</l>
                        <l>Their will and their deſire too in ſubjection,</l>
                        <l>And after him with their whole ſtrength purſue.</l>
                        <l>For to his beauty all things elſe are dim,</l>
                        <l>He is our Lord, and we muſt worſhip him.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="155">
                        <head>[155.]</head>
                        <l>For feare I ſay if any miſconſtruction,</l>
                        <l>I'l here turn off, and in few words expreſſe</l>
                        <l>My ſelfe herein, and ſo will by deduction,</l>
                        <l>Declare how ſhort all creature-comfort is;</l>
                        <l>Touching upon in a compendious ſtory:</l>
                        <l>My Love's bright beauty excellence and glory.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="1">
                        <pb n="57" facs="tcp:170222:35"/>
                        <head>1.</head>
                        <l>My tender youth hath found</l>
                        <l>An object for its Love,</l>
                        <l>Whereat I do not ſtound,</l>
                        <l>But all my powers move,</l>
                        <l>It for to gain,</l>
                        <l>Though with much pain,</l>
                        <l>And for to make it ſure,</l>
                        <l>I will not ſpare,</l>
                        <l>Nor do I care,</l>
                        <l>What ere I do endure.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="2">
                        <head>2.</head>
                        <l>It is no lower wight</l>
                        <l>That I do pitch upon,</l>
                        <l>My ſubject of delight</l>
                        <l>Is great <hi>Jehovah</hi>'s Son,</l>
                        <l>In him my minde</l>
                        <l>That ſweet doth finde,</l>
                        <l>That none with may compare,</l>
                        <l>By him I have</l>
                        <l>What ere I crave,</l>
                        <l>Though ne'r ſo good and rare.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="3">
                        <head>3.</head>
                        <l>My youth hath made a choice,</l>
                        <l>That I will not forgo,</l>
                        <l>Wherein I much rejoyce</l>
                        <l>And am affianc'd to,</l>
                        <l>Whom my deſire</l>
                        <l>Is ſet on fire</l>
                        <l>With ever to behold,</l>
                        <pb n="58" facs="tcp:170222:36"/>
                        <l>And whom I love</l>
                        <l>All things above,</l>
                        <l>Therefore in ſuit am bold.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="4">
                        <head>4.</head>
                        <l>Between my love and I</l>
                        <l>Is ſuch congruity,</l>
                        <l>That nought unto mine eye</l>
                        <l>Of like reſpect can be;</l>
                        <l>I do not prize</l>
                        <l>Nor hands, nor eys,</l>
                        <l>Nor ought elſe whatſoere,</l>
                        <l>My very life</l>
                        <l>Is but a ſtrife,</l>
                        <l>Not lov'd in his compare.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="5">
                        <head>5.</head>
                        <l>Ah, could my tongue but tell</l>
                        <l>The beauty of my love,</l>
                        <l>Wherein he doth excell,</l>
                        <l>Whate're doth breath or move,</l>
                        <l>There's none I'm ſure</l>
                        <l>That could endure</l>
                        <l>Him for to reſt ſhort of,</l>
                        <l>They would him love,</l>
                        <l>All things above,</l>
                        <l>Though now they at him ſcoffe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="6">
                        <head>6.</head>
                        <l>Could I but penſil out</l>
                        <l>That bright perfection rare,</l>
                        <l>That ſpreads it ſelf about,</l>
                        <l>His limbs and face ſo fair,</l>
                        <pb n="59" facs="tcp:170222:36"/>
                        <l>Each Readers heart</l>
                        <l>With Loves ſtrong dart,</l>
                        <l>Would ſuffer ſuch a wound,</l>
                        <l>So as that then</l>
                        <l>With lock and key</l>
                        <l>Were cloſely Priſoners bound.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="7">
                        <head>7.</head>
                        <l>My Love's ſo fair, ſo clear,</l>
                        <l>That neither Moon nor Sun</l>
                        <l>Do light or bright appear</l>
                        <l>In the Meridian,</l>
                        <l>No they are dim,</l>
                        <l>Compar'd with him,</l>
                        <l>Their beauty's 'clipſed quite</l>
                        <l>They hide their face,</l>
                        <l>As in diſgrace,</l>
                        <l>To ſuch a glorious light.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="8">
                        <head>8.</head>
                        <l>With glory he's array'd</l>
                        <l>As with a garment gay,</l>
                        <l>His beauty may be ſaid</l>
                        <l>To be the Angels day;</l>
                        <l>Heaven can nought</l>
                        <l>Afford that's ought,</l>
                        <l>If diſpoſſeſt of him,</l>
                        <l>For 't is his light</l>
                        <l>That makes it bright,</l>
                        <l>His preſence makes it trim.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="9">
                        <pb n="60" facs="tcp:170222:37"/>
                        <head>9.</head>
                        <l>O did you know the pow'r</l>
                        <l>Of his imperial brow,</l>
                        <l>And what delights do towre</l>
                        <l>Themſelves therein, and how,</l>
                        <l>Within your breaſt</l>
                        <l>You could not reſt,</l>
                        <l>Till you had ſeen that face,</l>
                        <l>Nor without doubt</l>
                        <l>Could live without</l>
                        <l>The preſence of his grace.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="10">
                        <head>10.</head>
                        <l>For why the Angels joy,</l>
                        <l>And Seraphims delight</l>
                        <l>Conſiſteth conſtantly</l>
                        <l>By being in his ſight,</l>
                        <l>Their happineſs</l>
                        <l>Is onely this</l>
                        <l>Him ever to behold,</l>
                        <l>Whereby deſire</l>
                        <l>Is ſet on fire,</l>
                        <l>And never waxes cold.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="11">
                        <head>11.</head>
                        <l>His ſmiles do make an Heaven,</l>
                        <l>His frowns produce an Hell,</l>
                        <l>For where his favour's given</l>
                        <l>No tongue their bliſs can tell;</l>
                        <l>His flaming ire</l>
                        <l>Begets a fire</l>
                        <l>That ever doth endure;</l>
                        <pb n="61" facs="tcp:170222:37"/>
                        <l>His bleſſed love</l>
                        <l>The Soul doth move</l>
                        <l>To joy and Peace moſt ſure.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="12">
                        <head>12.</head>
                        <l>No Angels tongue can tell,</l>
                        <l>Nor mortal ear ere heard,</l>
                        <l>Nor heart conceive or ſpell,</l>
                        <l>Thoſe joys that are prepar'd,</l>
                        <l>Prepar'd for them</l>
                        <l>That as a Gem</l>
                        <l>Do prize the Lord of Life,</l>
                        <l>Whom he will grace</l>
                        <l>With his bleſt face,</l>
                        <l>And marry as his Wife.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="13">
                        <head>13.</head>
                        <l>His nature's ſweet and milde,</l>
                        <l>Lovely, and full of grace,</l>
                        <l>Himſelf he ſo hath ſtil'd,</l>
                        <l>And 'tis read in his face,</l>
                        <l>His countenance</l>
                        <l>Doth much advance</l>
                        <l>His glories every where,</l>
                        <l>It is ſo humble</l>
                        <l>That none can ſtumble,</l>
                        <l>Say no acceptance's there.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="14">
                        <head>14.</head>
                        <l>For though he doth poſſeſs,</l>
                        <l>All things in Earth and Heaven,</l>
                        <l>Yet will he ne'rtheleſs</l>
                        <l>His grace to ſuch be given</l>
                        <pb n="62" facs="tcp:170222:38"/>
                        <l>As do him ſeek</l>
                        <l>With ſpirit meek</l>
                        <l>Though ne'r ſo vile and poor,</l>
                        <l>With real heart,</l>
                        <l>If they do part</l>
                        <l>
                           <note n="*" place="margin">In will and intention.</note> With ſin for evermore.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="15">
                        <head>15.</head>
                        <l>His countenance doth carry</l>
                        <l>In 't ſuch majeſtick grace,</l>
                        <l>That where 'tis Sin w'on't tarry,</l>
                        <l>But ſtraight acquits the place;</l>
                        <l>It's Pleaſures black</l>
                        <l>Their Beauty lack,</l>
                        <l>And melt away like Snow;</l>
                        <l>They ſhew then plain</l>
                        <l>But grief and pain,</l>
                        <l>But miſery and wo.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="16">
                        <head>16.</head>
                        <l>All worldly Pleaſures are</l>
                        <l>Compared with this delight</l>
                        <l>But as a Candle's blear</l>
                        <l>Unto the Suns clear light,</l>
                        <l>Or Glo-worms ſhine</l>
                        <l>In the day-time,</l>
                        <l>Yea and far viler too;</l>
                        <l>They then are ſorrows,</l>
                        <l>And deadly horrours,</l>
                        <l>Loathſom the Soul unto</l>
                        <pb n="63" facs="tcp:170222:38"/>
                        <l>A maſs of real wo.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="17">
                        <head>17.</head>
                        <l>I'll prove this ſtraight a truth</l>
                        <l>Unto your open view,</l>
                        <l>Come wanton luſtfull youth,</l>
                        <l>And give me anſwer now,</l>
                        <l>Your minde aſpires,</l>
                        <l>Being fill'd with fires,</l>
                        <l>And at great things doth aim,</l>
                        <l>But whoſe intent</l>
                        <l>Nobleſt deſcent,</l>
                        <l>(Of you or I) can claim?</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="18">
                        <head>18.</head>
                        <l>Again in Pleaſures Pool</l>
                        <l>Your youth doth bathe it ſelf,</l>
                        <l>But I my youth do ſchool,</l>
                        <l>In ſhunning of that elf;</l>
                        <l>I deal with joys,</l>
                        <l>Not ſuch vain toys,</l>
                        <l>A far they are below me,</l>
                        <l>I trade for Treaſures,</l>
                        <l>Not carnal Pleaſures,</l>
                        <l>The which vain youth do cow thee.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="19">
                        <head>19.</head>
                        <l>Thou ſerv'ſt a ſordid Luſt,</l>
                        <l>But I the God of Heaven;</l>
                        <l>And if obey thou muſt,</l>
                        <l>But to me freedom's given;</l>
                        <pb n="64" facs="tcp:170222:39"/>
                        <l>My joys do lie</l>
                        <l>With God on high,</l>
                        <l>My youths delights are there,</l>
                        <l>I in his Court</l>
                        <l>My ſelf diſport,</l>
                        <l>Where 'quaintance claime I dare.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="20">
                        <head>20.</head>
                        <l>Thou woo'ſt and ſu'ſt for love</l>
                        <l>To ſome inferiour Beauty,</l>
                        <l>I God himſelf do move</l>
                        <l>To him I tender duty,</l>
                        <l>Nor w'on't give o're</l>
                        <l>My Suit before</l>
                        <l>Himſelf I do obtain,</l>
                        <l>My heart in triall</l>
                        <l>Cann't take deniall,</l>
                        <l>My Soul muſt with him reign.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="21">
                        <head>21.</head>
                        <l>O tell me wanton youth,</l>
                        <l>What's thy delight to mine?</l>
                        <l>Wilt dare to ſay in truth,</l>
                        <l>My love exceeds not thine?</l>
                        <l>I know th' art ſham'd</l>
                        <l>It ſhould be nam'd</l>
                        <l>Upon that preſent day,</l>
                        <l>You bluſh to ſee</l>
                        <l>What fools you be,</l>
                        <l>And therefore nought can ſay.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="22">
                        <pb n="65" facs="tcp:170222:39"/>
                        <head>(22.)</head>
                        <l>But to proceed to ſpeak</l>
                        <l>Still further in his praiſe,</l>
                        <l>Whereto my heart's too weak</l>
                        <l>My eyes to view his Rayes,</l>
                        <l>His beauty bright</l>
                        <l>Allows no night</l>
                        <l>where ever it doth ſhine,</l>
                        <l>He doth impart</l>
                        <l>Unto that heart</l>
                        <l>A light and life divine.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="23">
                        <head>(23.)</head>
                        <l>He doth the ſoul revive</l>
                        <l>Where ever he doth come,</l>
                        <l>And gives it ſo to live</l>
                        <l>That it may keep a roome</l>
                        <l>For Majeſty,</l>
                        <l>Therein to lie,</l>
                        <l>And alwaies find a place,</l>
                        <l>He'll there keep Court</l>
                        <l>The ſoul diſport</l>
                        <l>With his moſt lovely face.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="24">
                        <head>(24.)</head>
                        <l>He doth the ſoul transform</l>
                        <l>Into his own likeneſs,</l>
                        <l>Doth it throughout adorn</l>
                        <l>With his bright glorious grace,</l>
                        <l>What found in him</l>
                        <pb n="66" facs="tcp:170222:40"/>
                        <l>Although but ſin</l>
                        <l>Shall in it (too) appear.</l>
                        <l>Tranſmutes &amp; changes</l>
                        <l>The ſoul eſtranges</l>
                        <l>From whats to Nature deare.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="25">
                        <head>(25.)</head>
                        <l>But not to ſoar above</l>
                        <l>The reach of tender youth</l>
                        <l>That ſlaves himſelf in love</l>
                        <l>Whom vain fond humours ſooth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </l>
                        <l>Whom up to lift</l>
                        <l>It is my drift</l>
                        <l>From off the dreggs of nature,</l>
                        <l>To fix on high</l>
                        <l>And him to eye</l>
                        <l>That is his bleſt Creator.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="26">
                        <head>(26.)</head>
                        <l>Moſt glorious is my Love</l>
                        <l>As you may plainly ſee</l>
                        <l>And doth't not me behove</l>
                        <l>Loyal to him to be?</l>
                        <l>Yes that I will</l>
                        <l>With all the skill</l>
                        <l>That I can make or gain</l>
                        <l>Whoſe work about</l>
                        <l>I will lay out</l>
                        <l>My ſelf with might and main.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="27">
                        <pb n="67" facs="tcp:170222:40"/>
                        <head>(27.)</head>
                        <l>Come Lovers I'll you tell</l>
                        <l>What privilege I have,</l>
                        <l>The which I will not ſell</l>
                        <l>For all Earths glory brave,</l>
                        <l>Although that glory</l>
                        <l>Shews none can ſtory</l>
                        <l>Whereof my love poſſeſt</l>
                        <l>Yet ſtill dare I</l>
                        <l>To him draw nigh</l>
                        <l>In love to be refreſht.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="28">
                        <head>(28.)</head>
                        <l>My love he is not coy</l>
                        <l>Though beautiful and fair</l>
                        <l>But fills my ſoul with joy,</l>
                        <l>It glads me to appear</l>
                        <l>Before his ſight,</l>
                        <l>For why? with might</l>
                        <l>Afreſh he doth me fill;</l>
                        <l>He ne'r me ſcorns,</l>
                        <l>But me adorns</l>
                        <l>According to his will.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="29">
                        <head>(29.)</head>
                        <l>While that low worthleſs beauty</l>
                        <l>That thou doſt ſo adore,</l>
                        <l>(Preſenting with ſuch duty)</l>
                        <l>Gives thee no thanks therefore</l>
                        <l>But makes thee ſerve</l>
                        <pb n="68" facs="tcp:170222:41"/>
                        <l>While like to ſtarve</l>
                        <l>Regarding not thy love</l>
                        <l>Whom thou draw'ſt nigh</l>
                        <l>(Oft ſhe is ſhie,</l>
                        <l>And doth far off remove.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="30">
                        <head>(30.)</head>
                        <l>With ſcorn ſhe oft thee flouts,</l>
                        <l>(The fruit of loath'd rejection)</l>
                        <l>Diſdains with churliſh pouts</l>
                        <l>Thy tenders of affection;</l>
                        <l>Though thoudoſt crouch</l>
                        <l>Her for to touch</l>
                        <l>With lowly bended knee,</l>
                        <l>Yet ſhe flies off</l>
                        <l>Doth at thee ſcoff,</l>
                        <l>She will not, no not ſhe:</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="31">
                        <head>(31)</head>
                        <l>O youth, what pains thou tak'ſt</l>
                        <l>Her love for to obtain,</l>
                        <l>Thy ſelf moſt ſervile mak'ſt,</l>
                        <l>Yet merits but diſdain;</l>
                        <l>But were I you,</l>
                        <l>I ne'r would ſue</l>
                        <l>For love ſo frivolous,</l>
                        <l>I would forſake,</l>
                        <l>No ſuit more make</l>
                        <l>To be rejected thus.</l>
                        <lg n="32">
                           <pb n="69" facs="tcp:170222:41"/>
                           <head>(32.)</head>
                           <l>Unto my Love I never did</l>
                           <l>Tender my hearts deſire,</l>
                           <l>But he forth with me anſwered,</l>
                           <l>And ſent me fire for fire,</l>
                           <l>What I him give</l>
                           <l>He doth receive,</l>
                           <l>And ſo in mutual love,</l>
                           <l>We each enjoy</l>
                           <l>Nor do we cloy,</l>
                           <l>Oh may I never move.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg n="33">
                           <head>(33.)</head>
                           <l>They that do give a heart</l>
                           <l>Unto the great Jehove,</l>
                           <l>May ſure themſelves that ſtart</l>
                           <l>He will not from his Love,</l>
                           <l>I'm ſure there's none</l>
                           <l>Can make their moane,</l>
                           <l>That they did to him tender,</l>
                           <l>Not onely part,</l>
                           <l>But their whole heart,</l>
                           <l>And he no love would render.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg n="34">
                           <head>(34.)</head>
                           <l>Think'ſt thou that Jeſus Chriſt</l>
                           <l>The Heir of Earth and Heaven,</l>
                           <l>By whom thy ſoul was prick't</l>
                           <l>And for't his life was given;</l>
                           <l>Thinks thou (ſay I)</l>
                           <pb n="70" facs="tcp:170222:42"/>
                           <l>That he'll deny</l>
                           <l>Thee love when thou doſt ſue,</l>
                           <l>Ah no he won't</l>
                           <l>His practice don't</l>
                           <l>Confirm that thing as true.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg n="25">
                           <head>(25.)</head>
                           <l>He'll bind his liſtning ear</l>
                           <l>When thou prefer'ſt a ſuit</l>
                           <l>Thy voyce he ſoon will hear</l>
                           <l>Nor will he then be mute,</l>
                           <l>He'll condeſcend</l>
                           <l>Unto that end</l>
                           <l>For which thy ſuit was made,</l>
                           <l>He will delight,</l>
                           <l>And glad thy ſpright,</l>
                           <l>Come therefore ben't afraid.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg n="36">
                           <head>(36.)</head>
                           <l>None ever made a proffer</l>
                           <l>Of any thing to him</l>
                           <l>That he refus'd their offer</l>
                           <l>Or flung their ſcorn on them</l>
                           <l>Ah no his grace</l>
                           <l>Doth ſoon give place</l>
                           <l>To entertain that love,</l>
                           <l>He'll anſwer them</l>
                           <l>With love again</l>
                           <l>That truth of heart doth move.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg n="37">
                           <pb n="71" facs="tcp:170222:42"/>
                           <head>(37.)</head>
                           <l>And youth when thou haſt gain'd</l>
                           <l>The perſon thou doſt ſue for,</l>
                           <l>Her love I mean obtain'd</l>
                           <l>(Which oft thy heart did rue for)</l>
                           <l>Thou art not ſure</l>
                           <l>It will endure</l>
                           <l>For Lovers minds are changing,</l>
                           <l>For all that love</l>
                           <l>Don't conſtant prove</l>
                           <l>(The mind is prone to ranging.)</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg n="38">
                           <head>(38.)</head>
                           <l>But ſure I am that love</l>
                           <l>That God doth give to his</l>
                           <l>Is conſtant, can't remove,</l>
                           <l>It everlaſting is,</l>
                           <l>The higheſt mountains</l>
                           <l>And loweſt fountains</l>
                           <l>Shall all firſt ceaſe to be,</l>
                           <l>The mighty hills</l>
                           <l>The deſert fields</l>
                           <l>Shall move into the Sea.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg n="39">
                           <head>(39)</head>
                           <l>Could my tongue tell the ſweets</l>
                           <l>The pleaſures of the mind</l>
                           <l>That with my ſoul oft meets</l>
                           <l>And I in love do find,</l>
                           <l>There is no ear</l>
                           <pb n="72" facs="tcp:170222:43"/>
                           <l>That could them hear,</l>
                           <l>But would be raviſh'd by 'em,</l>
                           <l>And then would ſpy</l>
                           <l>The vanity</l>
                           <l>In earthly things, and fly 'em.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg n="40">
                           <head>(40)</head>
                           <l>No place can me debar</l>
                           <l>The preſence of my love,</l>
                           <l>That bideth every where,</l>
                           <l>On earth beneath, above:</l>
                           <l>No company</l>
                           <l>Can me deny</l>
                           <l>My ſweet converſe with him;</l>
                           <l>Nor darkeſt night,</l>
                           <l>Hide from my ſight</l>
                           <l>His beauties clear and trim.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg n="41">
                           <head>(41)</head>
                           <l>This beauty can't decay,</l>
                           <l>(Though age your lov's defaces)</l>
                           <l>My joyes ſhall 'bide for aye,</l>
                           <l>In mutual loves embraces;</l>
                           <l>I ſhall enjoy,</l>
                           <l>Without annoy,</l>
                           <l>My love for evermore,</l>
                           <l>In that bright glory,</l>
                           <l>That none can ſtory,</l>
                           <l>Where Seraphims him adore.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg n="42">
                           <pb n="73" facs="tcp:170222:43"/>
                           <head>(42)</head>
                           <l>The care that now I take,</l>
                           <l>Is only ſo to live</l>
                           <l>A life, that love may ſpeak</l>
                           <l>To whom my love I give;</l>
                           <l>I care not I,</l>
                           <l>Who doth defie,</l>
                           <l>The ſervice of my love;</l>
                           <l>'I ſhall be my care,</l>
                           <l>No coſt to ſpare,</l>
                           <l>Sincere to him to prove.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg n="43">
                           <head>(43)</head>
                           <l>Commend, or diſ-commend</l>
                           <l>My lov's moſt ſtrict commands,</l>
                           <l>It nought to me doth tend,</l>
                           <l>My act not therein ſtands;</l>
                           <l>I will endeavour,</l>
                           <l>Now, and for ever,</l>
                           <l>His pleaſure for to do,</l>
                           <l>With heart and might,</l>
                           <l>Both day and night,</l>
                           <l>Who 'er's averſe thereto.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg n="44">
                           <head>(44)</head>
                           <l>I prize no love to his;</l>
                           <l>For what's all elſe to me?</l>
                           <l>In him's contain'd my bliſs;</l>
                           <l>Nought care I elſe to ſee:</l>
                           <l>'Tis he alone,</l>
                        </lg>
                        <pb n="74" facs="tcp:170222:44"/>
                        <l>That onely one</l>
                        <l>On whom my hear doth fix,</l>
                        <l>Him would I ſerve,</l>
                        <l>Not from him ſwerve,</l>
                        <l>Nor other ſervice mix.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="45">
                        <head>(45.)</head>
                        <l>Oh may my heart be true,</l>
                        <l>My will and my deſire,</l>
                        <l>Conſtantly him purſue,</l>
                        <l>And be to him entire,</l>
                        <l>Who is worthy</l>
                        <l>Of more than I</l>
                        <l>Am able for to give him,</l>
                        <l>But to his praiſe</l>
                        <l>Even all my dayes</l>
                        <l>I crave that I may live him</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="46">
                        <head>(46.)</head>
                        <l>A thouſand hearts had I</l>
                        <l>And every heart the might</l>
                        <l>The ſtrength and valiancy</l>
                        <l>Of thouſands, as his right</l>
                        <l>Them unto him</l>
                        <l>(My hearts dear gem)</l>
                        <l>Would I preſent and give,</l>
                        <l>And think this all</l>
                        <l>Yet far too ſmall</l>
                        <l>For him for to receive.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="47">
                        <pb n="75" facs="tcp:170222:44"/>
                        <head>(47.)</head>
                        <l>My tender youthful years</l>
                        <l>Hath long agoe forſaken</l>
                        <l>Earth's fading fooliſh toyes,</l>
                        <l>Of them farewel hath taken,</l>
                        <l>My tender youth</l>
                        <l>They may not ſooth,</l>
                        <l>For dead is my deſire</l>
                        <l>Unto its joyes</l>
                        <l>Such worthleſs toyes</l>
                        <l>That do ſo ſoon expire.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="48">
                        <head>(48.)</head>
                        <l>My tender years preſent</l>
                        <l>Their youthful ſtrength to him</l>
                        <l>With whole and joint conſent</l>
                        <l>To whom bright Sol is dim,</l>
                        <l>Whom I adore</l>
                        <l>For evermore</l>
                        <l>As Soveraign, Lord, and King,</l>
                        <l>Whom I'd reraiſe</l>
                        <l>In ſtrains of praiſe</l>
                        <l>And of his Glories ſing.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="conclusion">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170222:45"/>
                  <head>The Concluſion.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>NOw, young man lay to heart what I have ſaid,</l>
                     <l>Note well each matter I have here down laid,</l>
                     <l>Here's life and death preſented fairly to thee,</l>
                     <l>Be well advis'd they both alike do woo thee,</l>
                     <l>Onely there's this advantage, courſes ill</l>
                     <l>do ſwifteſt go, their path is down the hill;</l>
                     <l>But youth, thy breaſt is ſtrong, and youthful fire</l>
                     <l>May carry thee up-hill-wayes and yet not tire,</l>
                     <l>Put thy ſtrength to it, do not back retire,</l>
                     <l>Thy lungs being good, thy breath 'twill not expire,</l>
                     <l>Though down-hill-waies are eaſie, yet there's danger</l>
                     <l>In them, it is the practice of each ſtranger</l>
                     <l>Eas'ly to go, yea t' light and lead their Horſe</l>
                     <l>There where the Road doth prove a down-hill courſe:</l>
                     <l>But up-hill wayes do offer means to try</l>
                     <l>The Horſes courage, ſtrength and valiancy;</l>
                     <l>The rider he delights ſwiftly to force</l>
                     <l>A ſpeedy paſſage on an up hill courſe:</l>
                     <l>So young man, up-hill-waies preſent th' occaſion</l>
                     <l>To try thy youthful ſtrength without perſwaſion,</l>
                     <l>Come put on courage, put on manly might,</l>
                     <l>And mount this hill, the which preſents to ſight</l>
                     <l>A gallant proſpect, the bright Court of Heaven,</l>
                     <l>Where Saints and Angels, all the glorious ſeven</l>
                     <l>Do ſit, and chant the everlaſting praiſe</l>
                     <l>Of great Jehove, (deckt with bright glorious rayes)</l>
                     <l>Women and Children labour to fulfil</l>
                     <pb n="77" facs="tcp:170222:45"/>
                     <l>The puny wiſhes of their craving will;</l>
                     <l>'Tis childiſhneſs to follow inclination,</l>
                     <l>Effem'nacy to ſerve a fooliſh paſſion:</l>
                     <l>Theſe down-hill-waies though pleaſant ſweet &amp; ſooth,</l>
                     <l>yet don't become, but much abaſe thy youth:</l>
                     <l>Where's manly courage ſeen? up, up oppoſe,</l>
                     <l>Reſiſt, reſiſt th' invaſion of thy foes;</l>
                     <l>Ben't captivated by a head ſtrong will,</l>
                     <l>Fool'd by affection, led for to fulfil</l>
                     <l>A vain deſire, to gratifie a luſt</l>
                     <l>The ſoul and all her powers ſubſervient muſt:</l>
                     <l>Fie, fie young man, thy ſelf confine to reaſon,</l>
                     <l>And let grave precept thy weak judgment ſeaſon;</l>
                     <l>Let reaſon rule by Precepts, good direction</l>
                     <l>Thy ſtubborn will, and thy vain fond affection.</l>
                     <l>Art not aſham'd to let a humor lead thee?</l>
                     <l>Unruly luſts, untamed paſſions ride thee?</l>
                     <l>Is the heat of thy young blood degenerated</l>
                     <l>From all things good, to ill ſo cloſely mated?</l>
                     <l>Hath't loſt its ſtrength and vigor with its heat,</l>
                     <l>That it regards not worth, nor glory great?</l>
                     <l>Rouſe up thy ſoul young man, ben't ſo beſotted</l>
                     <l>To let a Pearle of price in dung be rotted;</l>
                     <l>Thy blood's waxt cold, obſtructed, it don't run</l>
                     <l>Quick in its channel, Glory is not won,</l>
                     <l>Nor once regarded by thee, ſure the courſe</l>
                     <l>Of nature's changed, yea, from bad to worſe.</l>
                     <l>Motives enow I'ave laid down to excite thee</l>
                     <l>Sin to oppoſe, and unto God invite thee;</l>
                     <l>Deſcribed during pleaſures to delight thee,</l>
                     <l>Set forth thine enemies in field to fight thee:</l>
                     <pb n="78" facs="tcp:170222:46"/>
                     <l>What can I more? What can I further do?</l>
                     <l>To gain upon the, which way ſhould I go?</l>
                     <l>Heaven and Glory I have laid thee down</l>
                     <l>(As Garland) thy victorious brows to Crown,</l>
                     <l>Pleaſures and joyes I have thee with preſented</l>
                     <l>That aye abides, and never ſhall be ended;</l>
                     <l>Beauty I have protraicted to thy eye,</l>
                     <l>For therein many a younglings heart doth lie,</l>
                     <l>I'ave ſhew'd thee how thy tender youth might gain</l>
                     <l>Either of theſe, or all of them attain;</l>
                     <l>Believe me youth if ought more lies in me</l>
                     <l>To do thee good, thy ſervant I will be;</l>
                     <l>How freely could I bear thee in mine arms,</l>
                     <l>But ah they'r weak and can't ſecure from harms,</l>
                     <l>I'll take thee by the hand and gently lead thee,</l>
                     <l>I'll go before thee and thy path out-tread thee:</l>
                     <l>But what am I? a poor weak ſorry Guide;</l>
                     <l>Miſtake me not! nor don't the ſpeech deride,</l>
                     <l>'Tis not of pride I ſpeak't, but out of love,</l>
                     <l>The bowels of my ſoul to youth doth move,</l>
                     <l>Fain would I have him 'quainted with his God,</l>
                     <l>That he might give him with himſelf abode:</l>
                     <l>Oh tender youth be rul'd, ſhake hands with ſin</l>
                     <l>And wanton courſes don't continue in,</l>
                     <l>They are not ſafe but full of deadly danger,</l>
                     <l>Or ſin with thee or God muſt be a ſtranger,</l>
                     <l>They will not lodge together in one breaſt,</l>
                     <l>For where ſin reigns Jehovah will not reſt.</l>
                     <l>And thou ſweet youth whoſe face is God-ward bent,</l>
                     <l>Who of all ſin and evil doſt repent,</l>
                     <l>I kindly greet thee, and if I did know thee,</l>
                     <pb n="79" facs="tcp:170222:46"/>
                     <l>I would endeavour more of God to ſhow thee;</l>
                     <l>Well howſo'er, thou to my heart art dear,</l>
                     <l>And as my body to my ſoul as near;</l>
                     <l>As true to God may thy heart be as mine</l>
                     <l>Is true to thee, that doſt to good incline;</l>
                     <l>Thou art to me as dear as an own brother,,</l>
                     <l>To Jeſus Chriſt likewiſe thou art no other,</l>
                     <l>He owns thee as a friend, a brother, wife,</l>
                     <l>More dearer to him art thou than his life,</l>
                     <l>For thee he dy'd, and lives, and now doth ſit</l>
                     <l>At Gods right hand, for thee to intercede;</l>
                     <l>And whom Chriſt Jeſus daignes himſelf to love,</l>
                     <l>With beſt affection, I dare boldly move,</l>
                     <l>But whereſoe'r thou art, my Counſel's this</l>
                     <l>To thee, perſiſt and follow on to bleſs,</l>
                     <l>In earneſt ſeek him and thou then ſhalt find him,</l>
                     <l>Which having done, with ſtrong affection bind him,</l>
                     <l>With conſtant ſuits ſalute his liſting ear,</l>
                     <l>Be confident and bold he will thee hear,</l>
                     <l>He loves an earneſt ſuiter at his Throne,</l>
                     <l>And that's the way to thrive in grace (or none)</l>
                     <l>Prayer gives to God his due, and ſhews the creature</l>
                     <l>How far it is below its bleſt Creator;</l>
                     <l>It brings the ſoul as firſt it ſelf to know</l>
                     <l>Its own frailty, ſo its God alſo,</l>
                     <l>And his abundant fulneſs of rich Treaſure</l>
                     <l>That he unto all creatures out doth meaſue,</l>
                     <l>It brings the ſoul with its bleſt God acquainted,</l>
                     <l>Works't off of ſin wherewith 'twas fouly tained,</l>
                     <l>'Tis ardent prayer unlocks the gates of heaven,</l>
                     <l>Nought God affords that is not by him given</l>
                     <pb n="80" facs="tcp:170222:47"/>
                     <l>Unto the ſoul that earneſtly doth ſue</l>
                     <l>With ardent fervent and affection true.</l>
                     <l>In prayer there is that rare rich ſecret good</l>
                     <l>That cannot be expreſt, that can't be underſtood;</l>
                     <l>Prayer is a jewel that I'd not forgoe</l>
                     <l>For all this world, I do eſteem it ſo;</l>
                     <l>Honor, wealth, fame, endowments laid at ſtake,</l>
                     <l>For precious prayer I would them all forſake.</l>
                     <l>The greateſt honors loſs it ſoon can gain,</l>
                     <l>And wealth procure, yea wealth that doth remain</l>
                     <l>For ever, when this world ſhall ceaſe to be,</l>
                     <l>This worlds beſt wiſdome is but foolery</l>
                     <l>To that which heaven, (by earneſt ſuit) doth give,</l>
                     <l>A praying temper may I e'r in-live.</l>
                     <l>Prayer is my ſouls delight, and I am mute,</l>
                     <l>To none ſave God can I preſent a ſuit;</l>
                     <l>Prayer's my refreſhment, and my greateſt joy,</l>
                     <l>I ne'r could ſay that e'r it did me cloy;</l>
                     <l>Though dayes and nights, yea weeks and months toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</l>
                     <l>I gave it all my ſoul, it joyes me ever.</l>
                     <l>Wer't not for prayer, what were this life unto me?</l>
                     <l>Wer't not for prayer, Divels would ſoon undo me,</l>
                     <l>Wer't not for prayer, the loathſome ſtink of ſin</l>
                     <l>Would poyſon me, and I ſhould die therein:</l>
                     <l>Wer't not for prayer, in doleful miſery</l>
                     <l>(By Gods permiſſion) ſhould I live and die;</l>
                     <l>Wer't not for prayer what comfort could I find?</l>
                     <l>What ſolace? what refreſhment to my mind?</l>
                     <l>Wer't not for prayer, how could I ought poſſeſs?</l>
                     <l>How could I bear my head up in diſtreſs.</l>
                     <pb n="81" facs="tcp:170222:47"/>
                     <l>Wer't not for Prayer, what were all comforts to me</l>
                     <l>Lawful? Indifferent things would quite undo me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>I have all things by Prayer, without I'ave nothing;</l>
                     <l>All things are joyous by 't, without 't, a loathing:</l>
                     <l>Prayer is my ſoul's beſt banquet, nought more joys me</l>
                     <l>then praying doth (you know what moſt then'noys me)</l>
                     <l>Sweet Prayer, I'll ever live and die in thee,</l>
                     <l>Till that time comes when thou ſhalt uſeleſs be;</l>
                     <l>Even till I'm ſwallowed up in his bleſt love,</l>
                     <l>And full poſſeſt thereof by thee, I'll move,</l>
                     <l>I'll move by thee, ſoaring upon the wings</l>
                     <l>Of Contemplation, until Death brings</l>
                     <l>Me to enjoy moſt fully, what I now</l>
                     <l>With longing heart, and true deſire forſue;</l>
                     <l>O bleſſed Majeſty! Thou, Three in One,</l>
                     <l>And One in Three, Thou art that One alone</l>
                     <l>That I deſire to be acquainted with.</l>
                     <l>To love, to ſerve, to praiſe, to worſhip, ſith</l>
                     <l>Thou art of during Goods, that bleſſed Fountain</l>
                     <l>Of ſtrength, and ſafety, that everlaſting mountain:</l>
                     <l>Thou giv'ſt moſt freely, yet haſt ſtill in ſtore</l>
                     <l>More than enough, to laſt for evermore.</l>
                     <l>Thou giv'ſt, and yet by giving haſt no leſs;</l>
                     <l>Thy ſtore increaſeth that thou doſt poſſeſs.</l>
                     <l>Lord, I am poor, and thou art full of riches,</l>
                     <l>Abound'ſt with wiſdom, Folly me bewitches:</l>
                     <l>Lord, I am weak, and thou art God of ſtrength,</l>
                     <l>Unleſs thou ſav'ſt, I periſh ſhall at length:</l>
                     <l>Thou do'ſt enjoyn the Rich, unto the poor</l>
                     <l>For to impart with ſome of their full ſtore;</l>
                     <pb n="82" facs="tcp:170222:48"/>
                     <l>And canſt thou, God of Riches, do ought leſs,</l>
                     <l>Then give to th' Needy what thou doſt poſſeſs</l>
                     <l>In great abundant<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> fulneſs? Ah! Canſt thou,</l>
                     <l>What thou enjoynſt thy Creatures to, tell how</l>
                     <l>For to deny thy ſelf? Oh! Wilt thov prove</l>
                     <l>So cruel, ſo unkind? Thou God of Love!</l>
                     <l>No ſure thou canſt not, thy delight's to give</l>
                     <l>Abundantly to man; crav'ſt that receive</l>
                     <l>Of thee he would, that everlaſting treaſure</l>
                     <l>Of thine conſiſting in true joy and pleaſure.</l>
                     <l>Miſerable am I! whither ſhould I turn</l>
                     <l>But unto Mercy? My deſires burn,</l>
                     <l>And long, and pine, thy Grace for to poſſeſs.</l>
                     <l>O thou in whom my life and pleaſure is,</l>
                     <l>Enlarge my Soul ſtill more, fill my deſires</l>
                     <l>With greater longings, with more ſtronger fires,</l>
                     <l>That ſtill my youth may make its boaſt of thee,</l>
                     <l>And thou mayſt ſtill delight thy ſelf in me,</l>
                     <l>That the whole ſtrength of theſe my yonger dayes</l>
                     <l>May be laid out and ſpent in thy bleſt praiſe.</l>
                     <l>As freely as thou gav'ſt my life to me,</l>
                     <l>So freely do I give my ſtrength to thee.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170222:48"/>
                  <p>A GLASS FOR VIRGINS.</p>
                  <p>Wherein alſo every SOUL may ſee, and from whence may be gathered, The Duty of every SOUL to CHRIST.</p>
                  <p>Held forth by a continued Parallel, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween, <hi>Virgins Behaviours to their Suitors,</hi> and <hi>The Christian Souls to Christ.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Unto which likewiſe the Author ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth himſelf.</p>
                  <p>By F. G.</p>
                  <q>Young Men and Maids, Old Men and Children<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Praiſe ye the Lord.</q>
               </div>
               <div type="about_the_author">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170222:49"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:170222:49"/>
                  <head>THE AUTHOUR Of this following POEM.</head>
                  <p>ALthough young Women are included and comprehended alwayes under the expreſsion, young Man (when Mankind is ſpoken to in general) becauſe things muſt be expreſt in the Melior which the ſacred Writ, as well as common Writ, witneſſes, which take in this one inſtance for many, <hi>Pſal. 119. Wherewithal ſhall a young man cleanſe his way,</hi> &amp;c? The
<pb facs="tcp:170222:50"/> Expreſsion comprehending both Sexes, young Women as well as young Men; ſo alſo have I all along, as much as I could, hinted to young Women, in, and through young Men, oft times alſo expreſſing the term more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deffinitely by the word <hi>youngling,</hi> which more clearly comprehends both Sexes: But for aſmuch as in the purſuit of a Diſcourſe we are bound to follow up matters in the melior, and to purſue Instances of the prime Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment: Therefore do I think good to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nex theſe following Lines to the former, wherein young Women ſhall be poſitively con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, and the state of young Women abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely ſpoke unto and parallel'd as the nature and condition of young Men was before, yet ſo, as reſerving that truth alwayes in my mind, and carrying of it along in my thoughts with me in this Diſcourſe, <hi>viz.</hi> that there is no distinction of Sexes with Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>And therefore, peradventure, I may mix
<pb facs="tcp:170222:50"/> Expreſſions of both Sexes in one (oft times) becauſe all is one in Chriſt.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>Herein will be what as well concerns the one Sex as the other, and that not abſolutely young Ones only, but the Aged alſo may find their Duty in ſome meaſure herein laid down.</p>
                     <p>Oh Reader, be ſober, and read with a heart ſolid and ſpiritual, and thy delight (I doubt not) then will be as great in reading, as mine is in writing and was when I expreſs'd from truth of Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence theſe things; thy good and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in God I heartily wiſh.</p>
                  </q>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170222:51"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:170222:51"/>
                  <head>A Glaſs for Virgins.</head>
                  <lg n="1">
                     <head>(1)</head>
                     <l>NOw Virgins unto you, to you I ſpeak,</l>
                     <l>To you directly now my Speech I turn;</l>
                     <l>For why? Your welfare I entirely ſeek,</l>
                     <l>And thereunto doth my deſier burn.</l>
                     <l>You are to me alike belov'd and dear,</l>
                     <l>And every whit as pretious as they were.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="2">
                     <head>(2)</head>
                     <l>Chriſt maketh no diſtinction, no more do I,</l>
                     <l>But good in any one I love and prize;</l>
                     <l>And whereſoever Grace I do eſpy,</l>
                     <l>Why in thoſe perſons my hearts pleaſure lyes.</l>
                     <l>Both Male and Foemale are alike to me,</l>
                     <l>When alike Principles I in them ſee.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="3">
                     <head>(3)</head>
                     <l>My heart is dead, moſt cold is my deſire</l>
                     <l>To any's friendſhip where no Grace I find;</l>
                     <l>Nought elſe but it can my affection fire,</l>
                     <l>Or ſomething that is like to it in kind.</l>
                     <l>Partial: Oh! May I never he in Love,</l>
                     <l>Nor ne'r affect where great Jehove don't move<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="4">
                     <pb n="90" facs="tcp:170222:52"/>
                     <head>(4)</head>
                     <l>Virgins attend: Note your denomination,</l>
                     <l>You prize the Name, Oh! ſee you live unto it:</l>
                     <l>Yo be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r your ſelves upon that appellation,</l>
                     <l>And ſo do I; what it beſpeaks let's do it:</l>
                     <l>Virgin ſpeaks purity, and ſinglneſſe,</l>
                     <l>All Chaſtity, and Soul retiredneſſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="5">
                     <head>(5)</head>
                     <l>A Virgins heart's within it ſelf compact</l>
                     <l>In unity, within it ſelfe's compoſed,</l>
                     <l>Each faculty's entire, and all exact;</l>
                     <l>Its happineſſe within it ſelfe's encloſed.</l>
                     <l>The heart's entire, th' affection whole and ſound,</l>
                     <l>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e will, deſire, unto themſelves are bound.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="6">
                     <head>(6)</head>
                     <l>A ſerene, quiet, calm, tranquillid frame</l>
                     <l>Of ſpirit doth a Virgins ſoul poſſeſs;</l>
                     <l>And being ſo, nought can it eas'ly maim:</l>
                     <l>Nor is there ought can make their joyes he leſs.</l>
                     <l>Affections in 'em are not parcel'd out,</l>
                     <l>Diſordered paſſions therefore can't them rout.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="7">
                     <head>(7)</head>
                     <l>A Virgins glory's to maintain this frame,</l>
                     <l>Tis this they make their buſineſs of life;</l>
                     <l>Their ſtrength's laid out for to maintain the ſame,</l>
                     <l>And ſo their ſouls preſerved are from ſtrife.</l>
                     <l>Thus is Virginity Angelical,</l>
                     <l>And to be priz'd the beſt eſtate of all.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="8">
                     <pb n="91" facs="tcp:170222:52"/>
                     <head>(8)</head>
                     <l>A Virgins honour lives in modeſt looks,</l>
                     <l>In ſober, and yet humble carriages,</l>
                     <l>A Virgins ſpirit no uncleanneſs brooks,</l>
                     <l>Hates of impurity all paſſages:</l>
                     <l>Her front ſhines with a kind of Majeſty,</l>
                     <l>True vertue may be ſeen with in her eye.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="9">
                     <head>(9)</head>
                     <l>This is a Virgins 'ſtate: I have defined</l>
                     <l>A Virgins Nature; I have pencil'd out</l>
                     <l>The Acts of them th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t have themſelves reſigned</l>
                     <l>Up thereunto, with their employment what about.</l>
                     <l>The which ſo worthy, and approved carriage,</l>
                     <l>Preſents them moſt deſirable in marriage.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="10">
                     <head>(10)</head>
                     <l>Chuſe to what perſon you will this apply,</l>
                     <l>To God himſelf, or to a lower creature,</l>
                     <l>For both in love the carriages do eye,</l>
                     <l>Deporture and demeanour in each feature.</l>
                     <l>To one, to both, this lovely you preſents</l>
                     <l>(Though God alone to pleaſe were your intents)</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="11">
                     <head>(11)</head>
                     <l>Oh Virgins know, Jehovah hath a Son,</l>
                     <l>The Heir of heaven and earth (alone) is he;</l>
                     <l>He's meek and milde, yet hath by courage won</l>
                     <l>Of the world, ſin, hell, and death, th' victory.</l>
                     <l>All pow'r, and might, and ſtrength's ſubjected to him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>He is ſo truly rich, nought can undo him.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="12">
                     <pb n="92" facs="tcp:170222:53"/>
                     <head>(12.)</head>
                     <l>This perſon's ſingle, and he ſeeks a wife</l>
                     <l>Amongſt the ſinful childeren of men,</l>
                     <l>He was ſo reall, that he gave his life</l>
                     <l>To gain their love, and to redeem them, when</l>
                     <l>They were ſold captives unto helliſh fiends,</l>
                     <l>Under darkneſs bound with everlaſting chains.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="13">
                     <head>(13.)</head>
                     <l>Which was ſuch love, that now a ſilent ſuit</l>
                     <l>('Tis thought) might be enough to gain their love,</l>
                     <l>Becauſe their lives are his in ſmall diſpute,</l>
                     <l>May cauſe affections unto him to move;</l>
                     <l>His Love was true and reall, no vain proffer,</l>
                     <l>No complement, no ſuperficial offer.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="14">
                     <head>(14.)</head>
                     <l>His blood did ſeal the truth of his affection,</l>
                     <l>His life throughout did teſtifie the ſame,</l>
                     <l>His neck he bowed under all ſubjection,</l>
                     <l>Nay he ſo much did do, I can't it name;</l>
                     <l>And may ſuch real love, be diſreſpected</l>
                     <l>While lighter's priſed, ſhall this be rejected?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="15">
                     <head>(15.)</head>
                     <l>If your hot blood may move your minds t' aſpire</l>
                     <l>To high preferment, by ſome noble match,</l>
                     <l>If honor, riches, pleaſure you deſire,</l>
                     <l>His love embrace, and his kind proffers catch;</l>
                     <l>For why? all theſe you meet withal in him,</l>
                     <l>Yea and much more whereto all theſe are dim.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="16">
                     <pb n="93" facs="tcp:170222:53"/>
                     <head>(16.)</head>
                     <l>He is a King and therefore can advance ye,</l>
                     <l>A King that tules and reignes for evermore,</l>
                     <l>A price upon his love therefore inhaunce ye,</l>
                     <l>He's full profeſſor of enduring ſtore;</l>
                     <l>If therefore you would unto honor riſe,</l>
                     <l>And happy be, accept his love, be wiſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="17">
                     <head>(17.)</head>
                     <l>The beſt of mortals can't advance ye ſo,</l>
                     <l>The greateſt Monarch can't that honor give,</l>
                     <l>The mightieſt Potentate, cannot beſtow,</l>
                     <l>That wealth and pleaſure that in him ye have;</l>
                     <l>Thoſe full contentments, thoſe delightful pleaſures,</l>
                     <l>Enduring ever with all peaceful treaſures.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="18">
                     <head>(18.)</head>
                     <l>Comprize the whole together, and 'tis this,</l>
                     <l>The God of Glory, heir of Earth and Heaven;</l>
                     <l>In whom all honor, pleaſure, wealth and blſis,</l>
                     <l>Doth bide and dwell: whoſe pretious blood was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</l>
                     <l>For mans Redemption; to the ſoul of man</l>
                     <l>Becomes a ſuiter, tries all waies he can.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="19">
                     <head>(19.)</head>
                     <l>To gain that love he over dearly bought,</l>
                     <l>To win that heart, for which he gave his life,</l>
                     <l>It to enjoy, that being loſt, he ſought</l>
                     <l>Eternally to make his glorious Wife:</l>
                     <l>His Grace doth ſue, Oh can our hearts deny,</l>
                     <l>Hold off, and ſo abaſe ſuch Majeſty.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="20">
                     <pb n="94" facs="tcp:170222:54"/>
                     <head>(20.)</head>
                     <l>Shall he to whom the glorious Queen of Heaven,</l>
                     <l>E'r ſues for favour, ſuit our worthleſs Love,</l>
                     <l>That are of whatſoever's good bereaven,</l>
                     <l>Shall he ſuit us, and we to him not move?</l>
                     <l>When he preſents himſelf can we be ſhie?</l>
                     <l>Ah ſhall he woo, and we his ſuit deny?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="21">
                     <head>(21.)</head>
                     <l>Maidens are wont much to regard their beauty,</l>
                     <l>They mayn't admit a blemiſh in the face,</l>
                     <l>Adorn themſelves, in carriages are haughty,</l>
                     <l>Are circumſpect leſt they incur diſgrace;</l>
                     <l>They heed to ſhape each action, work and carriage,</l>
                     <l>So as they mayn't prevent 'em in their marriage.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="22">
                     <head>(22.)</head>
                     <l>Oh Virgins! this Chriſt Jeſus looks upon,</l>
                     <l>A comely face with anſwerable attire,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe heart doth monut in contemplation,</l>
                     <l>Wh'are cautious what they will, what they deſire;</l>
                     <l>Whoſe ſpirits are ſublime, and ſcorn the earth,</l>
                     <l>And mount a loſt according to their birth.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="23">
                     <head>(23.)</head>
                     <l>May I explain my ſelf in this expreſſion,</l>
                     <l>By a comely face, a ſincere heart is meant,</l>
                     <l>Pure and humble, (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ear with this digreſſion,</l>
                     <l>Not a bare ſay ſo, and a complement</l>
                     <l>A gracious converſation is th' attire</l>
                     <l>Anſwering thereto, the which he doth deſire.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="24">
                     <pb n="95" facs="tcp:170222:54"/>
                     <head>(24.)</head>
                     <l>Our employment he'd have noble, and our thought</l>
                     <l>Raiſed above theſe low inferior things,</l>
                     <l>Our Virgin ſpirit he would not have fraught</l>
                     <l>With other matter, than what glory brings;</l>
                     <l>What would us ſuit, we may with ſcorn deny,</l>
                     <l>Or our hearts court; unto we may be ſhie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="25">
                     <head>(25.)</head>
                     <l>A Virgin ſtands upon her reputation,</l>
                     <l>A haughty ſcorn oft times doth fill her breaſt,</l>
                     <l>(Remember this in Chriſtian converſation)</l>
                     <l>She won't be in a ſluttiſh habit dreſt;</l>
                     <l>She bluſhes much at every misbehaviour,</l>
                     <l>And onely things commendable will ſavour.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="26">
                     <head>(26.)</head>
                     <l>Then Damſel hear, make conſcience of ſin;</l>
                     <l>Your reputation that doth fouly blemiſh,</l>
                     <l>Reject and ſcorn its paths to trample in,</l>
                     <l>Look e'r upon it with a look moſt ſquemiſh;</l>
                     <l>Abhor each though of ſin, it doth defile you,</l>
                     <l>Blemiſh your honor, doth of your glory ſpoyl you</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="27">
                     <head>(27.)</head>
                     <l>It marrs your beauty, and your comely looks,</l>
                     <l>It diſproportionates you throughout,</l>
                     <l>It makes you loathſome for Chriſt Jeſus brooks;</l>
                     <l>No ſin delighting ſoul, that thereabout</l>
                     <l>Doth ſpend its precious time, and trade in folly,</l>
                     <l>No, he delights and is a perſon holy.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="28">
                     <pb n="96" facs="tcp:170222:55"/>
                     <head>(28.)</head>
                     <l>Oh Virgins! ſhame to proſtitute your ſelves,</l>
                     <l>And give the ſtrenth of your young tender years,</l>
                     <l>Unto the ſervice of thoſe helliſh Elves,</l>
                     <l>That ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> delight unto your nature bears;</l>
                     <l>Remember that this Virgin-Prince looks on,</l>
                     <l>Sees e'ry act, though nere ſo ſecret done.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="29">
                     <head>(29.)</head>
                     <l>Oh! how you bluſh when young men do diſcry you</l>
                     <l>'Bout ſome uncivil, ſome immodeſt act;</l>
                     <l>You hang your heads, and from their ſight ſoon hie you,</l>
                     <l>Aſham'd you ſhould be ſeen in ſuch a fact;</l>
                     <l>You will not dare then once to ſhow your face,</l>
                     <l>So long as they continue in that place.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="30">
                     <head>(30.)</head>
                     <l>This Heaven-born heir, this Prince of great diſcent,</l>
                     <l>That ſeeks your love, that tenders you affection;</l>
                     <l>Veiws your immodeſt looks, your hearts intent,</l>
                     <l>Beholds full well to what you give ſubjection;</l>
                     <l>Bluſh you may at this, but ye cannot flee him,</l>
                     <l>He ſees you well, although you do not ſee him.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="31">
                     <head>(31)</head>
                     <l>Conſider Maidens, ſhould a worthy Suitor,</l>
                     <l>A well bred man, a man of noble birth;</l>
                     <l>Learned by vertue, having it his Tutor;</l>
                     <l>A comely perſon, owner of much wealth:</l>
                     <l>Should ſuch a one unto you make a proffer</l>
                     <l>Of love, and would you then contemne his offer.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="32">
                     <pb n="97" facs="tcp:170222:55"/>
                     <head>(32)</head>
                     <l>Would you before him, your ſelves miſ-behave?</l>
                     <l>No, for your reputations you would not,</l>
                     <l>Although he did not from you favour crave,</l>
                     <l>Nor tender your affection one jot.</l>
                     <l>For fear that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſhould be by him reported.</l>
                     <l>You were ill bred, to vanities beſotted.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="33">
                     <head>(33)</head>
                     <l>Think this in all the actions of your life,</l>
                     <l>For ſure Jehovah evermore doth eye ye,</l>
                     <l>He ſees what ills are in your natures <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ife,</l>
                     <l>In cloſeſt miſdemeanors he will ſpy ye.</l>
                     <l>Tremble hereat, for he will blaze the ſame,</l>
                     <l>More openly then by the trumpe of Fame.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="34">
                     <head>(34)</head>
                     <l>But further, Virgins, note your own behaviours,</l>
                     <l>Before, and to the perſon that doth tender</l>
                     <l>You hearty love, and daigns you many favours.</l>
                     <l>Conſider well I ſay, how you do render</l>
                     <l>Your ſelves unto him, alſo how before him,</l>
                     <l>You do behave ye (though you don't adore him.)</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="35">
                     <head>(35)</head>
                     <l>Your looks are ſober, carriages ſevere,</l>
                     <l>Modeſt your countenance, moſt chaſt your eye;</l>
                     <l>You heed your geſtures all (I mayn't ſay fear)</l>
                     <l>Leſt any abſurd carriage he ſhould ſpy.</l>
                     <l>You watch your words, &amp; ſtrictly gaurd your tongue,</l>
                     <l>And heed that wiſdom be your words among.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="36">
                     <pb n="98" facs="tcp:170222:56"/>
                     <head>(36)</head>
                     <l>All this you do, nor can ye do ought leſs,</l>
                     <l>Whether ye reſpect the perſon ye or no,</l>
                     <l>Becauſe your worth lies in your carriages,</l>
                     <l>For credit and much praiſe ye do gain ſo.</l>
                     <l>To e'ry perſon ye muſt give reſpect,</l>
                     <l>Shew carriage good, though him ye do reject.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="37">
                     <head>(37)</head>
                     <l>But how much more, yea, with what aggravations,</l>
                     <l>Of all this do ye (with much care) demean</l>
                     <l>Your ſelves to him, and to all his relations,</l>
                     <l>Whom of your beſt reſpects you worthy deem.</l>
                     <l>Yea, heed with patience, and much humbleneſs,</l>
                     <l>Yet very gladly what he doth, expreſs.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="38">
                     <head>(38)</head>
                     <l>You ſuit your ſelves with him (prizing his love)</l>
                     <l>The temper of his Spirit you delight in;</l>
                     <l>Your will doth cloſe with his, and you approve</l>
                     <l>What e'r he doth, and love what he hath right in<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>An Oneneſs ſo is made up in your Spirits,</l>
                     <l>Nought you can do, but you think he it merits.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="39">
                     <head>(39)</head>
                     <l>Behold the worthieſt Suitor that did ever</l>
                     <l>Make ſuit to Creature, Gods (ſole) eldeſt Son,</l>
                     <l>Doth to you, Virgins, his hearts love deliver,</l>
                     <l>Expreſly penned in what he hath done.</l>
                     <l>Had not he lov'd us, ſure he'd not have given</l>
                     <l>Himſelf to death, to purchaſe for us heaven.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="40">
                     <pb n="99" facs="tcp:170222:56"/>
                     <head>(40)</head>
                     <l>But may this love be termed; or a debt</l>
                     <l>That's to him due, that ſuffer'd ſo much for us?</l>
                     <l>We are the purchaſe of his Blood, and yet</l>
                     <l>He craves our love, when as he might abhor us.</l>
                     <l>He need not ſue our hearts, enough are his,</l>
                     <l>If that a debt by way of purchaſe is.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="41">
                     <head>(41)</head>
                     <l>About this matter let me reaſon with yee;</l>
                     <l>Were we not his, we could not be our own;</l>
                     <l>His en by debt (miſtake me not I prethee)</l>
                     <l>He was our Help when we were helpleſs grown.</l>
                     <l>When we were loſt, why then he did us find;</l>
                     <l>When none regarded us, he did us mind.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="42">
                     <head>(42)</head>
                     <l>When we were Captives bound unto the Devil,</l>
                     <l>And to partake with him in his ſad doom,</l>
                     <l>Sold unto Sin, and to each ſordid evil,</l>
                     <l>For our Redemption, then his Grace did come</l>
                     <l>To ſatisfie for us God's flaming ire,</l>
                     <l>And ſave our Souls from everlaſting fire.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="43">
                     <head>(43)</head>
                     <l>He drunk that Cup, which elſe we muſt have drunk;</l>
                     <l>He felt for us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> what elſe we ſhould have felt;</l>
                     <l>He plung'd thoſe deeps, wherein we ſhould have ſunk;</l>
                     <l>He bore that blow, that juſtice to us dealt.</l>
                     <l>For Mankind's ſafety he his life laid down,</l>
                     <l>And by his Death did purchaſe him a Crown.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="44">
                     <pb n="100" facs="tcp:170222:57"/>
                     <head>(44)</head>
                     <l>Now doth he ſue, 'tis but his own he ſues for,</l>
                     <l>It is the purchaſe of his blood he craves,</l>
                     <l>Denial here is that, the ſoul e'r rues for,</l>
                     <l>Who ſo complies thereto the ſame he ſaves;</l>
                     <l>Oh Virgins be ye ſolid, be ye wiſe,</l>
                     <l>Undone for ever ſhe's his ſuit denies.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="45">
                     <head>(45)</head>
                     <l>Be circumſpect, look well to your behaviours,</l>
                     <l>Return him for his love true love again,</l>
                     <l>Who doth not, Ingenuity not ſavours,</l>
                     <l>And muſt feel for it everlaſting pain;</l>
                     <l>He'as over-bought our love, who doth deny</l>
                     <l>To give't him, therefore's worthy aye to dye.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="46">
                     <head>(46)</head>
                     <l>Who doth accept his love, he makes his Wife,</l>
                     <l>Whom he doth cloath with Roabs of brighteſt glory,</l>
                     <l>Fills with all joy and peace, that's free from ſtrife,</l>
                     <l>Her ſtate's then ſuch, as Seraphims ſcarce can ſtory;</l>
                     <l>The beſt of Sains cannot (while here) conceive it,</l>
                     <l>Oh may we ever faithfully believe it.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="47">
                     <head>(47)</head>
                     <l>His Grace doth ſue that we'd hold forth in carriage,</l>
                     <l>That him we prize, and love and do adore,</l>
                     <l>That we would live as thoſe that expect marriage</l>
                     <l>With him, that rules and reigns for evermore;</l>
                     <l>Moſt reaſonable is this, then let's comply,</l>
                     <l>With mind and members, let us inſtantly.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="48">
                     <pb n="101" facs="tcp:170222:57"/>
                     <head>(48)<note place="margin">Parallel this with 34.</note>
                     </head>
                     <l>Oh! Virgin ſouls, can ye leſs worthy judge him,</l>
                     <l>Than carnal Lovers, that can gain reſpect,</l>
                     <l>At all hands from ye? Oh! how can ye grudge him</l>
                     <l>Thoſe common favours, and his love neglect?</l>
                     <l>Careful are ye to live as e'r before him,</l>
                     <l>And with your ſouls whole ſtrength do ye adore him.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="49">
                     <head>(49)<note place="margin">This with the 35.</note>
                     </head>
                     <l>Are ye e'r ſober, modeſt, chaſte and wiſe,</l>
                     <l>Reſpective in each geſture, each behaviour,</l>
                     <l>All this you'l be before your Suitors eyes,</l>
                     <l>Your words or actions may of no ill ſavour;</l>
                     <l>Solid you ſeem, not gariſh in your looks,</l>
                     <l>No ill diſcourſe your ear (at that time) brooks.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="50">
                     <head>(50)</head>
                     <l>Can ye do this for them? leſs worthy deem him,</l>
                     <l>That as your Love, ſo is your Lord and King;</l>
                     <l>Oh! can ye, can ye lightlier eſteem him?</l>
                     <l>Would ye far leſs reſpect unto him bring?</l>
                     <l>He eyes your carriages as well as they,</l>
                     <l>And thinks the ſame reſpect expect he may.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="51">
                     <head>Staffe 37 (51)</head>
                     <l>Do you love thoſe that are related to him?</l>
                     <l>Do you reſpect them as your Lovers kinne?</l>
                     <l>Think ye in love that your dear life ye owe him?</l>
                     <l>Spare ye for nought, his favour for to winne?</l>
                     <l>All this for lower Lovers ye will do,</l>
                     <l>To th' God of life and glory won't ye ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="52">
                     <pb n="102" facs="tcp:170222:58"/>
                     <head>(52)</head>
                     <l>Your Lovers voyſe is pleaſant to your ear,</l>
                     <l>No burden is the precept he layes on you,</l>
                     <l>You joy as much to do't, as it to hear,</l>
                     <l>Diſſent thereto in the leaſt tittle won't you;</l>
                     <l>The God of life for this ſame thing doth woo,</l>
                     <l>And ye will not for him comply thereto.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="53">
                     <head>(53)</head>
                     <l>Ah muſt he be denied, that which his Creature</l>
                     <l>May gain, and have with joy ful cheerful heart,</l>
                     <l>Expreſſed clear by many a lovely feature,</l>
                     <l>You will not ſtick, nor with his Love won't part</l>
                     <l>You will maintain that love on any terms,</l>
                     <l>Your ſouls with ſtrong reſolves themſelves ſo arms.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="54">
                     <head>(54)</head>
                     <l>This prince of Light, of Glory, Wealth and Peace,</l>
                     <l>Doth crave no more than what you to theſe give,</l>
                     <l>From evil courſes he would have you ceaſe,</l>
                     <l>And then a life conformed to him live;</l>
                     <l>Tender his Precepts, and obey his voyce,</l>
                     <l>Making his pleaſure your ſelected choyce.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="55">
                     <head>(55)</head>
                     <l>He craves reſpect as lower Lovers have,</l>
                     <l>And then your hearts affection he doth ſue for,</l>
                     <l>He gives true love, and he true love doth crave,</l>
                     <l>Which for to do, bid all the World adieu for;</l>
                     <l>This ſeems not harſh, for perſons whom ye love</l>
                     <l>You'll all forſake, and with them you will move.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="56">
                     <pb n="103" facs="tcp:170222:58"/>
                     <head>(56)</head>
                     <l>"Who ſo loves me, give ear unto my voyce,</l>
                     <l>"(Saies this bleſt heir) and note my precepts well,</l>
                     <l>"To keep my Heſts make evermore your choyce;</l>
                     <l>"And ever with you then I'll bide and dwell:</l>
                     <l>"Then unto you ſhall my affections move,</l>
                     <l>"To joy and be enjoy'd in mutual love.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="57">
                     <head>(57.)</head>
                     <l>"If you love me then keep you my Commands,</l>
                     <l>"And you ſhall loved be by the moſt high;</l>
                     <l>"Of me theſe were my Fathers ſtrickt Demands,</l>
                     <l>"And I obey'd his glorious Majeſty;</l>
                     <l>"Do thou obey, and his love eke and mine,</l>
                     <l>"Twiſted together, ſhall be both made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hine.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="58">
                     <head>(58.)</head>
                     <l>"Which when ye do, ſay then what is in Heaven</l>
                     <l>"That you deſire, or that your ſoul can crave,</l>
                     <l>"Which at your earneſt ſuit ſhall not be given?</l>
                     <l>"And at my hands moſt freely ye can't have?</l>
                     <l>"Enlarge your hearts, and crave what e'r you will,</l>
                     <l>I ready am, the ſame for to fulfill.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="59">
                     <head>(59.)</head>
                     <l>"Ask what you will and I'll accord unto it,</l>
                     <l>"For powers all in Heaven and Earth are mine,</l>
                     <l>"Soul ſpeak thy ſuit, I won't refuſe to do it,</l>
                     <l>"My ear and heart, ſhall thereunto incline;</l>
                     <l>"Thou canſt not ask what I can't to thee give;</l>
                     <l>Nor canſt thou fail becauſe I ever live<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="60">
                     <pb n="104" facs="tcp:170222:59"/>
                     <head>(60)</head>
                     <l>Soul, if thou lov'ſt him, then let theſe his words</l>
                     <l>Be ſweeter to thee than the honey dewes;</l>
                     <l>For whatſoever God or Heaven affords,</l>
                     <l>Of joy or peace, then to thy Soul acrews.</l>
                     <l>Thou then ſhalt have him here, and evermore</l>
                     <l>Poſſeſs him, after with all glorious ſtore.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="61">
                     <head>(61)<note place="margin">Staffe 38.</note>
                     </head>
                     <l>You ſuit you to the temper of your Love,</l>
                     <l>Are pleas'd and delighted with his pleaſure;</l>
                     <l>What e're he wills you to, you do approve,</l>
                     <l>And his deſerts out by your love you meaſure.</l>
                     <l>Demean your ſelves to Jeſus Chriſt but ſo,</l>
                     <l>(You ſhame to ſay to this Propoſal, No.)</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="62">
                     <head>(62)</head>
                     <l>But if you reckon upon life and bliſſe,</l>
                     <l>And that your Souls ſhould ſcape e'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>laſting fire,</l>
                     <l>Cloſe with his love, your ſafty elſe you miſſe,</l>
                     <l>And are fruſtrated in your hearts deſire.</l>
                     <l>Shall he enjoy you that did never love you,</l>
                     <l>Nor with a Lovers ſuit did ever move you?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="63">
                     <head>(63)</head>
                     <l>Ah! Sure he ſha'nt; it is for love you marry,</l>
                     <l>'Tis mutual love that joyneth hearts together:</l>
                     <l>If you do'nt like the perſon, you will tarry.</l>
                     <l>The caſe ſtands thus 'tween us and Chriſt; for either</l>
                     <l>We muſt love, prize, eſteem him above all,</l>
                     <l>Or '<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>is in vain him our lov'd Lord to call.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="64">
                     <pb n="105" facs="tcp:170222:59"/>
                     <head>(64)</head>
                     <l>He will not ſave that Soul that doth not love him:</l>
                     <l>Marriage can't be where perſons don't affect.</l>
                     <l>Can he unite with them thatn're did move him,</l>
                     <l>Nor ſhew unto him any love Reſpect?</l>
                     <l>Life is not dear where love hath taken place,</l>
                     <l>How do we prize? How do we ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e his Grace?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="65">
                     <head>(65)</head>
                     <l>Make we no Conſcience of a courſe of Sin?</l>
                     <l>Nor cool, nor quench, a ſoul or vain deſire;</l>
                     <l>Yet do we think his favou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> for to win,</l>
                     <l>And to be fill'd with that celeſtial fire?</l>
                     <l>That mutually doth joy and re-enjoy</l>
                     <l>Thoſe pleaſures in him, that can never cloy.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="66">
                     <head>(66)</head>
                     <l>Think we, Gods Son will marry with a Whore?</l>
                     <l>Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l he, that is the Heir of Earth and Heaven,</l>
                     <l>Abaſe himſelf ſo much, as evermore</l>
                     <l>To honour perſons of all good bereaven?</l>
                     <l>No, no, ſuch perſons as indulge in ſin,</l>
                     <l>He will not own (if live and die therein.)</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="67">
                     <head>(67)</head>
                     <l>I appeal to young Men (or to Virgins either)</l>
                     <l>Would they preſent her with true love, that's co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon</l>
                     <l>With every man? (The like to Virgins) Whether</l>
                     <l>Could ye love him that deals with every Woman?</l>
                     <l>Much leſs may any One expect to win</l>
                     <l>Chriſts favovr, that trades with delight in ſin.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="68">
                     <pb n="106" facs="tcp:170222:60"/>
                     <head>(68)</head>
                     <l>Know whatſoe'r thou art, that doſt commerce</l>
                     <l>Continually with ſin, that thou ſhalt never</l>
                     <l>See or behold, much leſs, with have converſe,</l>
                     <l>This glorious Bridgroome, that doth live fot ever;</l>
                     <l>No know thou that he's full of jealouſie,</l>
                     <l>And cannot brook filthy Adultery.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="69">
                     <head>(69)</head>
                     <l>And whenſoe'r thou hold'ſt commerce with ſin,</l>
                     <l>Thou play'ſt the whore, commit'ſt adultery.</l>
                     <l>Know whenſo'r vain thoughts are lodged in</l>
                     <l>Thy breaſt, thou loſeſt thy Virginity;</l>
                     <l>Sin doth pollute the heart, 'tis filthy, foul,</l>
                     <l>It doth corrupt, it doth defile the ſoul.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="70">
                     <head>(70.)</head>
                     <l>You know that 'tis abominable in nature</l>
                     <l>To have a bed defil'd, it moveth rage,</l>
                     <l>And ſtirreth up that fury in a creature,</l>
                     <l>That ſcarcely death and Divorce can aſſwage;</l>
                     <l>In noble perſons 'tis the greater ſin,</l>
                     <l>Noble I mean that wronged are therein.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="71">
                     <head>(71.)</head>
                     <l>Now 'tis a King, the everlaſting King,</l>
                     <l>That is concern'd in thee, O Virgin ſoul;</l>
                     <l>'Tis he whoſe worth the glorious Angels ſing,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe nature doth abhor a deed that's foul;</l>
                     <l>'Tis he, no leſs perſon that thou wrongeſt,</l>
                     <l>Thou art his intereſt, unto him belongeſt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="72">
                     <pb n="107" facs="tcp:170222:60"/>
                     <head>(72.)</head>
                     <l>They that defile his bed, are worthy ſure</l>
                     <l>Of a Divorce, and of perpetual pain,</l>
                     <l>Yea, they ſhall be confined to endure</l>
                     <l>Such horrors as for evermore remain;</l>
                     <l>Sin doth the ſoul divorce from God for ever,</l>
                     <l>Brings it to torment that expireth never.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="73">
                     <head>(73.)</head>
                     <l>To ſum up all, then take the matter thus,</l>
                     <l>Virgins while Virgins ſtrickt are and ſevere,</l>
                     <l>Becauſe their lives are then perſpicuous</l>
                     <l>Unto all perſons, great reſpective care</l>
                     <l>They have, that they miſcarry not in ought,</l>
                     <l>'Tis good behaviour makes them after ſought.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="74">
                     <head>(74.)</head>
                     <l>Their reputation lies in their behaviour</l>
                     <l>'Tis that gains love and meriteth reſpect,</l>
                     <l>'Tis that continueth their loveds favour,</l>
                     <l>That may they therefore by no means neglect;</l>
                     <l>O Virgin ſouls, remember all this carriage</l>
                     <l>To Jeſus Chriſt, who proffers to you marriage.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="75">
                     <head>(75.)</head>
                     <l>When Wives they are, and in ſtrickt wedlock bound,</l>
                     <l>Such carriage muſt they ſhape, as beſt may pleaſe,</l>
                     <l>Their ſpouſed Husbands, good Wives never ſtound</l>
                     <l>To give it to them, as their ſpouſal fees;</l>
                     <l>If thou art ſpouſed unto Chriſt, O ſoul,</l>
                     <l>Remember this each ſurgent I'll controule.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="76">
                     <pb n="108" facs="tcp:170222:61"/>
                     <head>(76.)</head>
                     <l>But as thou ſtand'ſt in hope to be his Bride<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thou ſtricktly art injoyn'd to live up to him,</l>
                     <l>To love him heartily and none beſide</l>
                     <l>(Conforming to his will doth ſtrongly woo him)</l>
                     <l>In holy life anſwer his gracious love,</l>
                     <l>And he will thine repay, won't from thee move.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="77">
                     <head>(77.)</head>
                     <l>O Virgin ſoul! triumph for to preſent</l>
                     <l>His Majeſty with love, and heart entire,</l>
                     <l>Be ſure let nothing fruſtrate thine intent,</l>
                     <l>In giving to him thy hearts ſtrongeſt fire;</l>
                     <l>Love is a moſt delightful bed to lie in,</l>
                     <l>Loves flames are very pleaſant for to fry in.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="78">
                     <head>(78.)</head>
                     <l>But to continue my old method ſtill,</l>
                     <l>My ſelf expreſſing in a varied verſe</l>
                     <l>For th' Readers pleaſure, therefore now I will</l>
                     <l>Put ſtop, and what remains therein rehearſe,</l>
                     <l>For both to th' outward and the inward man,</l>
                     <l>I'll ſuit my ſelf as pleaſant as I can.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:170222:61"/>
                  <lg n="1">
                     <head>(1)</head>
                     <l>NOw my ſelf for to expreſs, then</l>
                     <l>In a varied pleaſant ſtrain,</l>
                     <l>And ſpeak thoſe ſweets I taſte, when</l>
                     <l>Sin doth not my ſoul diſtrain,</l>
                     <l>O may my Song</l>
                     <l>And Lungs be ſtrong</l>
                     <l>To tell what joyes there do remain.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="2">
                     <head>(2)</head>
                     <l>As a Virgin ſworn to him,</l>
                     <l>Out of depth of true affection,</l>
                     <l>So am I, and won't forego him,</l>
                     <l>Nor refuſe his bleſt ſubjection;</l>
                     <l>Long may I ſtill</l>
                     <l>Maintain my will,</l>
                     <l>Obedient to his direction.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="3">
                     <head>(3)</head>
                     <l>I do my high glory count it,</l>
                     <l>To maintain a loyal heart</l>
                     <l>Unto his Grace; and think amount it,</l>
                     <l>Doth all treaſuries and art;</l>
                     <l>My ſoul doth crave,</l>
                     <l>Still to behave</l>
                     <l>Her ſelf ſo, ſhe mayn't with him part<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="4">
                     <pb n="110" facs="tcp:170222:62"/>
                     <head>(4)</head>
                     <l>He's my choice, and I do prize him</l>
                     <l>Above all the world can ſhow me;</l>
                     <l>My Soul's raviſh'd when ſhe eyes him,</l>
                     <l>And all things are then below me.</l>
                     <l>She never meets,</l>
                     <l>With ſuch like ſweets,</l>
                     <l>As ſhe conceivs when he doth know me.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="5">
                     <head>(5)</head>
                     <l>As a Virgin, may I ever</l>
                     <l>My ſelf humble chaſtily carry,</l>
                     <l>That diſpleaſe him I may never,</l>
                     <l>That abide he may, and tarry</l>
                     <l>With me till th' time,</l>
                     <l>In th' glorious clime,</l>
                     <l>My worthleſs Soul doth with him marry.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="6">
                     <head>(6)</head>
                     <l>Ah! might I ever feel the power</l>
                     <l>Of his ſoul-melting love,</l>
                     <l>That all ſweet, and no whit ſower,</l>
                     <l>Ah then! how then ſhould I move?</l>
                     <l>With quick'ned pace,</l>
                     <l>I'd keep no place,</l>
                     <l>Till in the Courts of great Jehove.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="7">
                     <head>(7)</head>
                     <l>O the ſweets, the joyes, the pleaſures,</l>
                     <l>That the ſoul doth taſte and find!</l>
                     <pb n="111" facs="tcp:170222:62"/>
                     <l>O the honors, glories, treaſures,</l>
                     <l>That are poſſeſſed by that mind;</l>
                     <l>That Chriſt doth love,</l>
                     <l>All things above,</l>
                     <l>Shewing not it ſelf to him unkind!</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="8">
                     <head>(8)</head>
                     <l>There's no earthly ſweet can gloſs it,</l>
                     <l>Nor ſhade it forth in meaneſt hue;</l>
                     <l>There's no Artiſt that can doſe it,</l>
                     <l>Or dimention give it true;</l>
                     <l>No, reaſon's blind</l>
                     <l>And cannot find</l>
                     <l>Wherewith to ſet it forth to view.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="9">
                     <head>(9)</head>
                     <l>May my Virgin-ſoul enjoy him,</l>
                     <l>He ſhall lodge between my breaſts,</l>
                     <l>And that nothing may annoy him,</l>
                     <l>I'll keep watch while he there reſts.</l>
                     <l>He ſhall to me,</l>
                     <l>Moſt welcome be,</l>
                     <l>So long as in my Soul he gueſts.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="10">
                     <head>(10)</head>
                     <l>He knows my heart, I'd not diſpleaſe him</l>
                     <l>(Willingly) to ſtire his ire,</l>
                     <l>But when I do, why then I leaſe him:</l>
                     <l>Yet then his patience I admire.</l>
                     <l>For when that I,</l>
                     <l>To him draw nigh,</l>
                     <l>With Grace he doth me re inſpire.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="11">
                     <pb n="112" facs="tcp:170222:63"/>
                     <head>(11)</head>
                     <l>He's my joy, my crown, my glory,</l>
                     <l>Such contentment he affords,</l>
                     <l>As an Angel's Pen can't ſtory,</l>
                     <l>Far beyond all ſenſe of words,</l>
                     <l>Him for to gain,</l>
                     <l>I fear no pain,</l>
                     <l>Nor care I for the edge of Swords.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="12">
                     <head>(12)</head>
                     <l>For What's life to the enjoyment</l>
                     <l>Of his ever-bleſſed-love?</l>
                     <l>The ſweets of life oft prove a cloyment,</l>
                     <l>Oft a loathing: I'll not move.</l>
                     <l>I'll take no pain,</l>
                     <l>Them for to gain,</l>
                     <l>Becauſe they meer deceits do prove.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="13">
                     <head>(13)</head>
                     <l>But my joyes in love laſt ever,</l>
                     <l>When both light of Moon and Sun</l>
                     <l>Shall ceaſe to be; yea, ceaſe for ever:</l>
                     <l>And fierce fire this world ſhall burn.</l>
                     <l>Say then ſhall ſhe,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Lo! This is he,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That I have waited ſo upon.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="14">
                     <head>(14)</head>
                     <l>Behold him now with glory claded,</l>
                     <l>And his great Majeſtick train;</l>
                     <pb n="113" facs="tcp:170222:63"/>
                     <l>Oh now how my ſoul is gladded!</l>
                     <l>I ſhall with him e'r remain;</l>
                     <l>With Angels I</l>
                     <l>Eternally,</l>
                     <l>Shall praiſe him in melodious ſtrain.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="15">
                     <head>(15)</head>
                     <l>Then will he in glory throne me,</l>
                     <l>With his ſacred Majeſty,</l>
                     <l>He as his dear ſpouſe will own me,</l>
                     <l>I ſhall bide e'r in his eye;</l>
                     <l>And live by love,</l>
                     <l>Of him above,</l>
                     <l>In heaven to all eternity.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="16">
                     <head>(16)</head>
                     <l>To ſuch a Spouſe as thus'll advance me,</l>
                     <l>Say, may I be coy to love?</l>
                     <l>At what a rate ſhould I inhaunce me?</l>
                     <l>With what hatred to ſin move?</l>
                     <l>How coy how ſhie</l>
                     <l>With heart defie</l>
                     <l>It? ſeing he me terms his Dove.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="17">
                     <head>(17)</head>
                     <l>My noble ſpirit ſcorns the abaſement,</l>
                     <l>Of the ſervitude of ſin,</l>
                     <l>It puts her beauties to defacement,</l>
                     <l>Blaſts and ſtains her Lilly-skin;</l>
                     <l>Far may it be,</l>
                     <l>The refore from me,</l>
                     <l>Its pleaſures by ſuch loſſe to win.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="18">
                     <pb n="114" facs="tcp:170222:64"/>
                     <head>(18)</head>
                     <l>No, Sin avaunt, my Soul doth loath thee,</l>
                     <l>Thou doſt of my beauty ſpoyl me:</l>
                     <l>Begon, I ſay, my Soul abhors thee,</l>
                     <l>Thy pleaſures do not pleaſe, but toyl me.</l>
                     <l>Thy delights,</l>
                     <l>My Soul affrights,</l>
                     <l>And thy eaſe doth greatly foyl me.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="19">
                     <head>(19)</head>
                     <l>My Virgin-Soul's of noble birth,</l>
                     <l>Of his royal blood deſcended,</l>
                     <l>That is Lord of Heaven and Earth,</l>
                     <l>Therefore ought to be attended</l>
                     <l>As ſuch a One,</l>
                     <l>And not alone</l>
                     <l>Left, for to be by Sin offended.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="20">
                     <head>(20)</head>
                     <l>O Sin! Thou baſe foul Blackamore,</l>
                     <l>Hell's off-ſpring, and by Devils nurſt,</l>
                     <l>That part'ſt from God for evermore,</l>
                     <l>And mak'ſt all like thy ſelf accurſt.</l>
                     <l>Thou deadly Foe,</l>
                     <l>Far from me go,</l>
                     <l>Into my preſence do not thruſt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="21">
                     <head>(21)</head>
                     <l>For I am a Maid of Honour,</l>
                     <l>Spouſed to God's only Son.</l>
                     <pb n="115" facs="tcp:170222:64"/>
                     <l>O're whom he diſplayes his Banner,</l>
                     <l>And thereby hath conqueſt won,</l>
                     <l>'Tis vain for you,</l>
                     <l>Therefore to ſue,</l>
                     <l>Bold Sin avaunt, away be gone.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="22">
                     <head>(22)</head>
                     <l>A chaſte Virgin I muſt keep me,</l>
                     <l>Till the day of Marriage come;</l>
                     <l>At which time, who ſhould, may reap me,</l>
                     <l>Giving unto me this doom.</l>
                     <l>True haſt thou been</l>
                     <l>(As I have ſeen,)</l>
                     <l>To me, Therefore enjoy me, Come.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="23">
                     <head>(23)</head>
                     <l>I know my Lord views my behaviour,</l>
                     <l>I know he notes each geſture well,</l>
                     <l>He regards how I him favour,</l>
                     <l>And whereupon my thoughts do dwell:</l>
                     <l>My Virgin Soul,</l>
                     <l>If ſhe prove foul,</l>
                     <l>Muſt with the Devils bide in Hell,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="24">
                     <head>(24)</head>
                     <l>Loathſome Sin, begone far from me,</l>
                     <l>I dare not lodge thee: No I dare not,</l>
                     <l>Thou brings grief and horrour to me;</l>
                     <l>Therefore for thy joyes I care not.</l>
                     <l>Thy ſeeming joyes,</l>
                     <l>Are ſad annoyes,</l>
                     <l>Shall I tranſgreſſe? O No, I dare not<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="25">
                     <pb n="116" facs="tcp:170222:65"/>
                     <head>(25)</head>
                     <l>What, ſhall ſuch a one as I am,</l>
                     <l>Proſtitute my ſelf to ſin?</l>
                     <l>No its pleaſures I defie? em,</l>
                     <l>And its waies to perſiſt in,</l>
                     <l>No I may not.</l>
                     <l>Give place a jot,</l>
                     <l>For the diſgrace of my kin.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="26">
                     <head>(26)</head>
                     <l>Shall I dare my ſelf to baniſh.</l>
                     <l>From my ſouls own native ſoyle?</l>
                     <l>For ſins ſake that ſoon doth vaniſh,</l>
                     <l>And my choiceſt pleaſures ſpoyl?</l>
                     <l>Oh! ſure I won't;</l>
                     <l>Therefore ſin don't,</l>
                     <l>Diſturb me more, keep ſuch a coyle.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="27">
                     <head>(27)</head>
                     <l>Shall I be bewitcht with evil,</l>
                     <l>So as with my God to part?</l>
                     <l>Give my members to the Devil,</l>
                     <l>And with them my mind and heart?</l>
                     <l>Make I no more,</l>
                     <l>To play the whore,</l>
                     <l>And from my loved Lord to ſtart?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="28">
                     <head>(28)</head>
                     <l>No, I am a Virgin ſworn,</l>
                     <l>Unto great Jehovahs Son,</l>
                     <pb n="117" facs="tcp:170222:65"/>
                     <l>And my Virgin ſoul doth ſcorn,</l>
                     <l>To be by another won;</l>
                     <l>To do an act,</l>
                     <l>Or any fact,</l>
                     <l>That he prohibits to be done.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="29">
                     <head>(29)</head>
                     <l>For life's to me far leſs dearer,</l>
                     <l>Than his pretious matchleſs love,</l>
                     <l>Oh that that I were to him nearer,</l>
                     <l>In his glorious houſe above,</l>
                     <l>Him to enjoy</l>
                     <l>Without annoy,</l>
                     <l>And never more from him to move.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="30">
                     <head>(30)</head>
                     <l>Deareſt Lord, let me for ever,</l>
                     <l>While I in this vale abide,</l>
                     <l>Be diſſerted of thee never,</l>
                     <l>What ills e'r ſo me betide;</l>
                     <l>So ſin ſhall be</l>
                     <l>Abhor'd by me,</l>
                     <l>And all its motives e'r deny'd,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="31">
                     <head>(31)</head>
                     <l>For thy looks revive my ſpirit,</l>
                     <l>And new life therein inſpire,</l>
                     <l>They do give me to inherit,</l>
                     <l>Thoſe delights that I deſire;</l>
                     <l>Accord to me,</l>
                     <l>Let me them ſee,</l>
                     <l>And ſo they never ſhall expire.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="32">
                     <pb n="118" facs="tcp:170222:66"/>
                     <head>(32)</head>
                     <l>Moſt Endeared, let me woo thee,</l>
                     <l>With thy Counſels me to guide,</l>
                     <l>And that nothing may undo me,</l>
                     <l>Let thy preſence with me bide;</l>
                     <l>And ſo ſhall I</l>
                     <l>Moſt conſtantly,</l>
                     <l>Keep cloſe unto thy foot and ſide.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="publishers_advertisement">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170222:66"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THere is another Book, compoſed (long ſince) by this ſame Authour, ſhewing the Souls Converſation with God, Contemplation in God, Supplication to God, Adoration of God; and containing ſeveral Love Sonnets and Ejaculations, breathed forth according to the ſeveral Eſtates and Conditions of the Soul; laid down in ſeveral Odes as Occaſion permitted the Authour.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Wherein, and whereby may be underſtood the manner of the Authours, Life and Carriage from time to time, which the Authour gave forth to the Preſs long ſince, whatever is become of it, to the which this Quotes, and would be of great uſe to go along with this.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
